Yoshio nozawa
よしお のざわ
The Central Research Institute's
中央研究所の
International Research Center for International Studies
国際総合研究センター
will begin.
始まる。
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
王宇監督をお迎えしましょう
to give us a round of applause.
拍手を送ります。
Good evening, everyone.
皆さん、こんばんわ。
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
王宇監督をお迎えしましょう
Today we are pleased to invite you to our Earth Institute
今日は皆さんを地球研究所にご招待します。
This special review researcher Dr. Zhao Feng
今回の特別査読研究者 趙峰博士
come talk to us
私たちに話しに来てください
Our little friend of the earth, the moon
私たちの地球の小さな友達、月
then let me briefly introduce
それでは簡単に紹介させていただきます
Background information of our presenter today
今日のプレゼンターの背景情報
Dr. Zhao was born in Hualien
趙博士は花蓮で生まれました。
He graduated from the Department of Physics, National Taiwan University.
国立台湾大学物理学科を卒業。
after that in san diego
その後サンディエゴで
UCCNL gets a Ph.D. in Earth Sciences
UCCNL が地球科学の博士号を取得
That's also NASA.
それもNASAです。
many years of service
長年の勤務
Then in 2006 he
それから彼は2006年に
That's because Taiwan is running a space agency
それは台湾が宇宙機関を運営しているからです
undertake a large project
大規模なプロジェクトに着手する
So we are very happy to have him back
だから私たちは彼が戻ってきてとても嬉しいです
He is also at Chuo University
彼も中央大学にいます
Before coming to Academia Sinica
中央研究院に来る前に
He is the Dean of the Faculty of Earth Sciences at Central University
彼は中央大学地球科学学部長です
for a few years
数年間
He has been in Academia Sinica for four years
彼は中央研究院に4年間在籍しています
Dr. Zhao's expertise is in Earth and planetary dynamics
Zhao 博士の専門知識は地球と惑星の力学です。
gravity
重力
And geophysics, seismology, etc.
そして地球物理学、地震学など。
This is also the research scope of our Earth Institute
これは私たちの地球研究所の研究範囲でもあります
he is on earth
彼は地球上にいます
he also does
彼もそうします
Because of the background I just introduced
先ほどご紹介したような背景があるため、
He also does space vehicle geosciences
彼は宇宙船の地球科学も行っています
In terms of research, of course, there is no need to drop the order here
もちろん、研究に関しては、ここで注文を外す必要はありません。
But he is invaluable
でも彼はかけがえのない存在だ
Apart from this research
この研究とは別に
he also for
彼もまた
I think there is a scientist in China
中国に科学者がいると思う
It is the Chinese version of Scientific American
サイエンティフィック・アメリカンの中国語版です
Often write Chinese articles there
そこでよく中国語の記事を書きます
Also published a book on the ancient and modern world between heaven and earth
天と地の間の古代と現代の世界についての本も出版
If you are interested in his speech
彼のスピーチに興味があるなら
What we can look forward to in the future is the scientific people
では、今後期待できるのは科学者です。
He also often writes
彼もよく書いています
Okay then I'll stop talking nonsense
わかりました、くだらない話はやめます
Please listen carefully to this moon
この月に耳を傾けてください
Is this sound okay?
この音大丈夫ですか？
Can
できる
sure
もちろん
Thank you Vice President
副社長、ありがとう
Just now the vice president mentioned that those are research expertise
先ほど副社長は、それは研究の専門知識だと言いました。
Of course he's really good at storytelling over here.
もちろん、彼はストーリーテリングが本当に上手です。
Today is
今日は
Today is Uncle Zhao telling a story
今日は趙おじさんが物語を語る日です
Today we're on a meet-the-neighbors tour
今日は近所の人に会うツアーです
This neighbor is our neighbor
この隣人は私たちの隣人です
moon
月
We all know this neighbor
私たちは皆、この隣人を知っています
Every day actually you have the chance to see him
実際、毎日あなたは彼に会う機会があります
But thousands of years of human civilization have seen thousands of years
しかし、人類の文明は何千年も続いてきた
I really don't know him
私は本当に彼のことを知りません
until recently so to speak
いわばつい最近まで
Only after the development of science did we slowly understand him
科学が発達して初めて、私たちはゆっくりと彼のことを理解できるようになりました
Today I will of course talk in depth
今日はもちろん深くお話します
things we already know
私たちがすでに知っていること
But it's really just fur
でも本当はただの毛皮なんだよ
real
本物
We can really say that we are to our neighbors
私たちは隣人に対して本当にそう言えます
I still don't know
まだ分​​かりません
let's take a look
見てみましょう
Everyone see me here
みんなここで私を見てるよ
actually asked a lot of questions
実際にたくさんの質問をしました
i hope i have time
時間があればいいのですが
Can cover these problems
こんな悩みもカバーできる
Some questions are not easy to ask
簡単に尋ねられない質問もあります
Because really we know so little
なぜなら実際のところ、私たちはほとんど知らないからです
This is what we are all familiar with
これは私たち全員がよく知っていることです
the moon looks like this
月はこんな感じです
After a whole month's cycle
丸一ヶ月のサイクルの後
We can see this before and after
これは前後でわかります
if there is no cloud
雲がなければ
It can be said that we only know
私たちだけが知っているとも言える
only see its ID
そのIDのみを参照してください
we don't really understand it
私たちはそれを本当に理解していません
This can be obtained from
これは次から取得できます
I'll be back here later
後でここに戻ってきます
Our understanding of the moon from the ancients
古代人から受け継いだ月についての私たちの理解
you can help it imagine
想像してみてもいいでしょう
Really, actually, I feel full
本当に、本当に、お腹がいっぱいになった気分です
I feel sympathy for the ancients
古代人に同情する
they really don't know
彼らは本当に知らない
what's going on in this world
この世界で何が起こっているのか
then we now think
それから私たちは今考えます
Primary school textbooks tell us
小学校の教科書が教えてくれる
But the ancients really didn't know
でも古代人は本当に知らなかった
They are the moon that sees the sun
彼らは太陽を見る月です
Cycle like this every day for centuries
何世紀にもわたって毎日このように循環します
He really doesn't know what's going on
彼は何が起こっているのか本当に分かっていない
The same should be true for the moon
月も同じはずだ
to the ancients
古代人へ
Ours is in the poetry, in the legend
私たちのものは詩の中に、伝説の中に
And these cosmology legislation
そして、これらの宇宙論は、法律の中で
all have the shadow of the moon
すべては月の影を持っています
But it's just a superficial impression
でもそれは表面的な印象にすぎない
So of course this is over
だからもちろんこれで終わり
this meeting
この会議
another example
もう一つの例
For example, in the Yijing
たとえば『易経』では、
These universal philosophies that everyone is familiar with
誰もが知っている普遍的な哲学
two of them
そのうちの2人
The moon is one of the two instruments of nutrition
月は栄養をもたらす2つの道具のうちの1つです
This is when we used to try to understand these things
私たちがこれらのことを理解しようとしていた時代です
invented some
いくつかを発明した
we know it's not true
私たちはそれが真実ではないことを知っています
not scientifically correct ideas
科学的に正しくない考え
We are now going to look at it from a scientific point of view
これから科学的な観点から見ていきます
when our neighbor
私たちの隣人が
The first thing to actually ask is that we just call it the moon.
実際に最初に尋ねるべきことは、それを単に月と呼んでいるかということです。
you know it's a ball
あなたはそれがボールであることを知っています
In fact, I really want to ask why is it a ball?
実際のところ、なぜそれがボールなのか尋ねたいのですが。
Do you think this will be a problem?
これは問題になると思いますか?
Isn't the earth also a ball?
地球も球体じゃないの？
Isn't the sun also a ball?
太陽も球ではないでしょうか？
yes these things are balls
はい、これらはボールです
Actually, one physics question we can really ask is
実際、私たちが実際に尋ねることができる物理学の質問の 1 つは、
why is this stuff a ball
なぜこれがボールなのか
There's actually a lot of physics behind this.
実はこれには多くの物理学が関係しています。
I point it out just to say
言いたいだけで指摘してる
when we really want to understand this neighbor
この隣人を本当に理解したいとき
We don't even know what it looks like
それがどのようなものであるかさえ私たちにはわかりません
don't know why
なぜだかわかりません
It's all taken for granted
それはすべて当然のことです
Is it a matter of course?
それは当然のことですか？
because in the solar system
なぜなら太陽系では
there are many smaller things
小さいものがたくさんあります
The so-called small these few examples
いわゆる小規模なこれらのいくつかの例
For example, there is a little star
たとえば、小さな星があります
This is a photo taken with a real small spaceship
これは本物の小型宇宙船で撮った写真です
or the moon of mars
あるいは火星の月
Mars has two small moons
火星には小さな衛星が2つある
one of them looks like this
そのうちの1つはこんな感じです
this is very small
これはとても小さいです
It's about tens of kilometers in size.
大きさはおよそ数十キロメートル。
Such a thing is really not round.
そんなものは本当に丸くない。
We say a circle is not a ball
円はボールではないと言います
This little thing is really not a ball
この小さなものは実際にはボールではありません
That is to say, in Sun Creek
つまり、サンクリークでは
or in this universe
あるいはこの宇宙の中で
when something comes together
何かが集まるとき
Only when it is large enough will it become spherical
十分に大きくなって初めて球形になります
the moon is big enough
月は十分大きいです
Something about a few hundred kilometers will probably
おそらく数百キロメートルくらいの距離にあるでしょう。
something this big
こんなに大きなもの
It will probably naturally become spherical
自然に球状になるんだろうな
The reason behind that is actually very simple
その背後にある理由は実は非常に単純です
It's the same as water flowing downhill.
坂を下る水と同じです。
lowest failure state
最低の故障状態
This is what it means
これが意味するところです
It has turned into this tree in one fell swoop and the rain comes out
一気にこの木になって雨が降る
I'm the reason behind this
この背後にある理由は私にあります
That is to say you see the sun as a ball
つまり、太陽をボールとして見るということです
The moon is a ball, the earth and we are also balls
月は球、地球も我々も球
In fact, behind
実は後ろに
physical reason
物理的な理由
it's just saying
それはただ言っているだけです
point out one
一つ指摘する
things we take for granted
私たちが当たり前だと思っていること
It's not a matter of course
当たり前のことではない
ok let's move on to some
さて、いくつかに移りましょう
related to the moon
月に関係するもの
just on the surface we can
表面的にはできるだけです
Some interesting phenomena observed
いくつかの興味深い現象が観察されました
I'll go into it later and talk about some comparisons
後ほど詳しく説明し、いくつかの比較について説明します
A more in-depth understanding later
後でさらに深く理解する
Let me tell you one
先講一個
I want to spend a few minutes on this
これについて数分時間を費やしたいと思います
Tell everyone this long-winded
長々としたことをみんなに伝えてください
our this
私たちのこれ
The so-called force in life
生活中間的所謂力
Whether it is the calendar
カレンダーにしても
powerful anyway
とにかく強力な
This thing is done in units of years
こういうのは年単位でやるんだよ
we all know
私たちは皆知っています
There is a so-called Gregorian calendar
いわゆるグレゴリオ暦があります
There is a so-called lunar calendar
いわゆる太陰暦というものがあります
The Gregorian calendar follows the sun
太陽暦は太陽に従う
according to the sun
太陽によると
We are all familiar with this force by now
私たちは今ではこの力についてよく知っています
is the power of the sun
太陽の力です
Something to do with the moon
月と何か関係があるのか
nothing
なし
it really doesn't matter at all
それは本当にまったく関係ありません
For example we are in
たとえば、私たちは
This is like the old days
これは昔のことのようだ
A kind of traditional society will use
ある種の伝統的な社会は、
one of determination
決意のひとつ
One way is called two-style solar term
一つの道を二流節気といいます。
right
右
I might give you this now
これを今あげてもいいかもしれません
this self
この自分
ask yourself this
これを自分に問いかけてください
See the second type of solar term
二番目の種類の二気節を参照
Do you think it's positive or negative?
それはポジティブだと思いますか、それともネガティブだと思いますか？
This is actually going to
これは実際にそうなります
Now you have to define what Yang Li is
次に、Yang Li が何であるかを定義する必要があります
what is yin force
陰の力とは何ですか
I'm talking about Yangli now
今はヤンリーのことを話しているんだ
we usually get that day
私たちは通常その日を迎えます
The moon force is the yang force
月の力は陽の力です
And you know the day is fixed by the sun
そして、一日は太陽によって決まることを知っています
right
右
one day to the next one day to the next
ある日から次の日へ ある日から次の日へ
It's natural that it takes a day
1日かかるのは当たり前
use the sun
太陽を使う
Does it have nothing to do with the moon?
月とは関係ありません
such a force
そのような力
Yangli
ヤンリー
The second type of solar terms is Yin force
二番目のタイプの太陽用語は陰の力です
Is it really Yangli?
本当にヤンリーなのか？
the answer is
答えは
Because you need to know the function of the 24 solar terms
二十四節気の働きを知る必要があるため
it actually puts the sun
実際に太陽を当てます
We orbit the sun more than 365 days
私たちは365日以上太陽の周りを回っています
Divide that day into 24 parts
その日を24分割する
Each one is about 15 days more like this
それぞれ約15日こんな感じです
That's it
それでおしまい
it divides the year
それは年を分ける
This has nothing to do with the moon
月とは関係ありません
right
右
Look at these words in these 24 solar terms
二十四節気のこれらの言葉を見てください
you can also see
あなたも見ることができます
It's full of temperature effects
温度の影響がいっぱいです
The effect of humidity
湿度の影響
Effect of sunlight
日光の影響
Relationship to the middle of the sun's orbit
太陽の軌道の中心との関係
None of the words have anything to do with the moon
どの言葉も月とは何の関係もありません
one more you can know
あなたが知ることができるもう一つ
In fact, all you know is
実際、あなたが知っているのは次のことだけです
these solar terms
これらの太陽用語
The month and date are the same every year
月と日は毎年同じです
it didn't run around
走り回らなかった
For example, tomb-sweeping day
たとえば、お墓掃除の日
April 4th or 5th
4月4日か5日
there is a new day
新しい日があります
because our days have no years
私たちの日々には年がないから
That day beats a little bit
あの日は少しだけ鼓動する
basically it's the same day
基本的には同日です
All these solar term days are on the calendar
これらすべての新学期の日はカレンダーに載っています
It's the same day every year
毎年同じ日だよ
Does this already tell you that this is the Gregorian calendar?
これで、これがグレゴリオ暦であることがわかりましたか?
Because the moon doesn't matter, right?
だって月は関係ないですよね？
even if you think about it
考えても
What is the purpose of thrift
倹約の目的は何ですか
actually an agricultural society
実は農業社会
He wants to know me every year
彼は毎年私のことを知りたがります
what time do you want to do
何時にしたいですか
what you do is agriculture
あなたがやっていることは農業です
That agriculture has nothing to do with the moon
農業は月とは何の関係もない
right
右
You have to completely follow the law of the sun
太陽の法則に完全に従わなければなりません
to farm
農場へ
you survive
あなたは生き残る
If you use what moon
どの月を使うなら
Cloudy and sunny
曇りのち晴れ
If you plant, do your farming
植えるなら農業もやれ
You'll be almost 20 in a few years
あと数年で20歳近くになるよ
because the time is wrong
時間が間違っているから
If you look at it from this angle
この角度から見ると
Calendar
カレンダー
It's Nongli
ノンリです
I'm not wrong, there shouldn't be
私は間違っていない、そんなはずはない
Really, if you want to do farming
本気で農業をやりたいなら
don't think about the moon
月のことは考えないでください
you really have to follow the sun
本当に太陽に従わなければなりません
All these things follow the sun
これらすべてのものは太陽に従う
That is to say, even without the moon
つまり月がなくても
this is still right
これはまだ正しい
So how does this follow
それで、これはどのように続きますか
anything to do with the moon
月と関係のあること
Does it have something to do with sound?
音と何か関係があるのでしょうか？
Absolutely not
絶対違う
So this is Yangli
これがヤンリーです
Then don't we really have something called sound power?
では、私たちには音響力と呼ばれるものが本当に存在するのではないでしょうか？
Do you know what Nongli and Yangli are?
ノンリとヤンリって知っていますか？
Of course we have the so-called sound
もちろんいわゆるサウンドもあります
Sound itself doesn't really matter.
音自体は特に問題ありません。
It's just a fun and a convenience
それはただの楽しみであり便利です
Do you remember when the moon was full last month
先月満月だったのを覚えていますか
Actually the moon is full again
実はまた満月です
you just have this
あなたはこれを持っているだけです
there is such a rule
そういうルールがあります
Actually it's not doing anything
実際には何もしていない
Unless you are some aquatic creature by the sea
あなたが海辺の水生生物でない限り
to do your life cycles according to the tides and stuff like that
潮流などに応じてライフサイクルを行うこと
or you don't
それともあなたはしませんか
appointment has nothing to do with you
約束はあなたとは何の関係もありません
So that's a chestnut
それは栗です
We know of some very conscious
私たちは非常に意識の高い人たちを知っています
like three verses, right?
3節くらいですよね？
that's a chestnut
それは栗です
That's why
それが理由です
you are using the legislation of the chestnut
あなたは栗の法律を利用しています
inside that stand
あのスタンドの中には
These chestnuts
この栗
You know it's different every year, right?
毎年違うのはご存知ですか？
because it is not chestnut
栗ではないので
the ancient people
古代の人々
or now you get
または今ならわかります
Is there any so-called peasant power?
いわゆる農民力というのはあるのでしょうか？
it is counted in black chestnut
黒栗で数えられます
so it becomes saying
だからこう言うことになる
The knotter is jumping up and down on that stand
ノッターはそのスタンドの上で飛び跳ねている
different every year
毎年違う
Because the two stand cannot be combined
2つのスタンドを組み合わせることができないため、
Because this is not an integer multiple
これは整数倍ではないので、
you will definitely be jumping around
あなたは間違いなく飛び跳ねることになるでしょう
so this
したがって、この
I put this first
これを最初に置きました
Let me remind you of the role of the moon in this
この中での月の役割を思い出させてください
really so
本当にそうです
For example, when we talk about the Lunar New Year
たとえば、旧正月について話しましょう
In fact, the word does not seem to be wrong
実際、その言葉は正しいようです。
Is January 1st the lunar year?
1月1日は旧暦ですか？
Because it's the lunar calendar?
旧暦だから？
Is the lunar calendar the solar calendar?
太陰暦は太陽暦ですか？
When we talk about the lunar year, we actually talk about the lunar year
私たちが旧暦について話すとき、実際には旧暦について話します。
this is just a thought
これは単なる考えです
There is indeed such a
確かにそのようなことはあります
can be fun
楽しいかもしれない
here
ここ
We are still looking at some of the moon
私たちはまだ月の一部を見ています
some of what we can see
私たちが見ることができるものの一部
some interesting things on the surface
表面上のいくつかの興味深いこと
you will notice this heaven
あなたはこの天国に気づくでしょう
There are two eyes and a smiley face
目が 2 つあり、笑顔があります。
Do you remember this day?
この日のことを覚えていますか？
Photos taken on December 2, 2008
2008 年 12 月 2 日に撮影された写真
This is when the sun is going down
これは太陽が沈む頃です
Of course it's Crystal
もちろんクリスタルですよ
This is the lunar calendar and I ran to this position
これが旧暦でこの位置まで走った
That day, this day, this time, here
あの日、この日、この時、この時ここ
Isn't it a lot of fun to have a cartoon performance here
ここで漫画のパフォーマンスをするのはとても楽しいではありませんか
let's pay attention
注意しましょう
when you see the moon
月を見るとき
This is Yueya we saw
私たちが見たユエヤです
because the sun is here
太陽がここにあるから
So there's no problem with the light here
だから、ここの光には問題はありません
In fact, it seems that there are also
実はこんなこともあるようです
The places that are not illuminated are not illuminated
光らないところは光らない
Look closely, there seems to be something
よく見ると何かあるようだ
right
右
I'm sure someone has this experience every day.
きっと誰かが毎日このような経験をしていると思います。
Take a closer look at the time when the weather is clean
天気が良い時期をよく観察してください
When you look at Yueya
ユエヤを見ると
It seems that the audio and video can also see the whole moon
動画では月全体も見えるようです
This is in the photo
これは写真にあります
Because it can be exposed to light for a longer time
長時間光に当たる可能性があるため、
see more clearly
もっとはっきり見える
Let me show you another example
別の例をお見せしましょう
This is also in the photo
これも写真に写ってます
take longer
もっと時間がかかる
It really seems like the sun is shining here
ここは本当に太陽が輝いているようです
Not here at all
全然ここにいない
but here it seems
しかし、ここではそう思われます
But it's bright anyway
でもとにかく明るい
faintly visible
かすかに見える
This is a clearer example
これはより明確な例です
this is not the full moon
これは満月ではありません
Sputnik
スプートニク
It was taken from the spaceship
宇宙船から採取されたものです
dark side of the moon
月の暗黒面
This moment is when it shines on the dark side of the moon
月の裏側で輝くこの瞬間
That is to say, when the sun actually shines on Naimian
つまり、太陽が実際にナイミアンを照らすとき
I can actually see it glowing
実際に輝いているのがわかります
This is actually
これは実際には
i think a lot
たくさん考えます
Everyone has this experience
誰もがこの経験を持っています
This is actually called a ground photo
これは実際には地上写真と呼ばれます
is the earth
地球です
This is light bouncing several times
これは何度か光を反射する
The sun shines directly on the bright side of the moon
太陽は月の明るい面を直接照らします
yes
はい
it can't see this side
こちら側が見えない
But why is this side slightly brighter?
しかし、なぜこちら側が少し明るいのでしょうか？
It's the sun's light that shines on the earth
地球を照らす太陽の光です
the earth reflects it back
地球がそれを反射して返す
brighten it up
明るくして
Then the reflected light
すると反射光が
reflected back into your eyes
あなたの目に反射して戻ってくる
Or the one seen in the machine
または機械に見られるもの
very interesting
とても興味深い
Light and shadow have gone several times
光と影は何度も消えた
I can still vaguely see it
まだぼんやりと見えます
this is not your illusion
これはあなたの幻想ではありません
is really there
本当にそこにいます
Taiwan has relatively humid air
台湾は空気が比較的湿っているため、
when you see this phenomenon
この現象を見ると
not many
あまり多くない
OK there are still some phenomena
OK、まだいくつかの現象があります
probably more or less familiar
おそらく多かれ少なかれよく知られている
date and time
日時
one thing is very interesting
とても興味深いことが一つあります
yes it's a coincidence
はい、それは偶然です
It is the moon and the sun in our sky
それは私たちの空の月と太陽です
Of course the sun is big
もちろん太陽は大きいです
but the sun is far away
でも太陽は遠い
But to observers on Earth
しかし地球上の観測者にとっては
these two circles
この2つのサークル
almost as big
ほぼ同じ大きさ
sometimes a little farther a little closer
時には少し遠くに少し近くに
will be big
大きくなるでしょう
that's basically the same size as it really is
基本的には実際と同じサイズです
it's a coincidence
それは偶然です
That's why if you encounter
だからこそ、もし遭遇したら
Just enough to cover the whole land from the sun
土地全体を太陽から覆うのに十分な量
Sometimes the distance is slightly worse
距離が少し悪くなることもあります
it will be slightly smaller
若干小さくなります
more and more more and more real
ますますますます現実的になる
This is very obvious to tell you this coincidence
この偶然を言うと非常に明白です
At this distance on Earth these two things appear
地球上のこの距離にこれら 2 つのものが現れます
It's really as big as a conspiracy
それは本当に陰謀と同じくらい大きなものです
Here is an example
ここに例があります
If seen from space
宇宙から見たら
this is earth
ここは地球です
This is the astronaut on the International Space Station
これは国際宇宙ステーションの宇宙飛行士です
Full time of a day captured by a camera
カメラが捉えた一日の全時間
an image on earth
地球上のイメージ
a shadow
影
In other words, this black lump is the shadow of the moon.
つまり、この黒い塊は月の影なのです。
That is to say, the people in this
つまり、この中の人たちは、
When I looked up to the sky, I saw this
空を見上げたらこんなのが見えた
This is because the earth is also rotating
地球も自転しているからです
The moon is running, the sun is running too
月も走る、太陽も走る
This shadow is of course in the net mother's
この影はもちろんネット母の中にあります
direction is moving fast
方向が速く動いている
So someone at a certain location will see
したがって、特定の場所にいる誰かが見るでしょう
The moon is here to block the out of tune
月は調子の狂いをブロックするためにここにある
that is to say on earth
つまり地球上で
Who is the person who sees the moon and sun?
月と太陽が見える人は誰ですか？
people in this strip
このストリップの人々
I don't know where this is going at this time
現時点ではどうなるかわかりません
Call this strip something like this
このストリップに次のような名前を付けます
people down here look up
ここにいる人々は上を見上げます
then you will see this
そうすればこれが見えます
This is what we look at from another angle
別の角度から見るとこうなります
This thing I think everyone compares
これは誰もが比較すると思います
In fact, everyone understands
実は誰もが理解している
just bring it
ただ持ってきてください
recall
想起
OK
OK
This is a fast motion video
これは高速アクションビデオです
that's one month
それは1か月です
like this for a month
このまま一ヶ月
I miss everyone
みんながいなくて寂しい
It can be said that I have seen too much, right?
見すぎとも言えますね。
But when you slow down, maybe you see something that you don't normally notice
でも、速度を落とすと、普段は気付かないものが見えるかも知れません
For example, what was your first feeling when you saw this
たとえば、これを見たときに最初に感じたことは何ですか?
Of course, we all understand the ups and downs.
もちろん、私たちは皆、浮き沈みを理解しています。
Why does it seem to be dangling?
ぶら下がっているように見えるのはなぜですか?
this dangling is not it dangling
このぶら下がりはぶらぶらではないですか
because when we were on earth
なぜなら私たちが地球にいたとき
Did you know it's orbiting the earth?
それが地球の周りを回っていることをご存知ですか？
The orbit around this one is not a circle, it's an earth circle.
この軌道は円ではなく、地球の円です。
It's a little earthy round
ちょっと土っぽい丸いです
This is known to oil lamp mechanics
これはオイルランプの整備士には知られています
If the orbit is round
軌道が丸い場合
How can it be a little slower when you are far away?
遠くにいるともう少し遅くなるのはなぜですか？
Walks a little faster when approached
近づくと少し早く歩く
That is to say, when we look here
つまり、ここを見ると
The moon is actually sometimes faster and sometimes slower
月は実際には速いときもあれば遅いときもあります
then you speed it up
それからあなたはそれを加速します
Sometimes I can see a little more of this side
時々、もう少しこちら側が見えることがあります
Sometimes I can see a little bit more from the angle
斜めから見るともう少し見えることもあります
i shake it together
一緒に振ってみます
just see it like it's dangling
ぶら下がっているように見てください
not he shaking
彼は震えていない
just the way we see it
まさに私たちが見るように
It's been changing a little bit like this
こんな感じで少しずつ変わってきました
That's actually the main reason I'm posting this for everyone to see.
実はそれが、私がこれを皆さんに見てもらえるように投稿する主な理由です。
not this
これではない
but want to ask everyone
でもみんなに聞きたい
what is the most important thing you see
あなたが見ている最も重要なものは何ですか
except he is round
彼が丸いこと以外は
we already know he's round
私たちは彼が丸くなったことをすでに知っています
a little wobbly
少しぐらつく
know him
彼を知っています
you know what's most important to you what you see
あなたにとって何が一番重要か知っていますか？
The most important thing you really see is
あなたが実際に見る最も重要なことは、
where you didn't see
あなたが見ていなかった場所
did you notice you didn't see behind him
彼の後ろが見えていないことに気づきましたか
He is just a face for you to see
彼はあなたに見せるためのただの顔です
He won't let you look behind
彼はあなたに後ろを見させてくれない
this strange thing
この奇妙なこと
You see I brought props
小道具を持ってきたのがわかりますか
This is our earth
ここは私たちの地球です
we live up there
私たちはそこに住んでいます
Just earn and die
ただ稼いで死ぬだけ
Earn a lap a day
1日1周を稼ぐ
the moon is here
月はここにあります
27 days to transfer full circle
一周転送まで27日
Because there is also the relationship between the angle of the moon and the sun
月と太陽の角度の関係もあるので
So the sun and the moon move
こうして太陽と月は動く
So more than 27 days is not really the cycle we see
つまり、27 日を超えるサイクルは実際には私たちが見ているサイクルではありません
We really use the cycle of cloudy and sunny to be 29 and a half days
曇りと晴れのサイクルは実際には 29 日半です。
So there are two kinds of moons
つまり、月には2種類あるのです
about 30 days about 29 days
約30日 約29日
Because the average is 29 and a half days
平均は29日半なので
this is not important
これは重要ではありません
it is important to say
言うことが重要です
this moon is orbiting
この月は周回しています
It doesn't matter that the earth is spinning on our own
地球が勝手に回っているなんて関係ない
when it is winding
巻いているとき
it never showed you the back
それは決してあなたに背中を見せませんでした
it goes around like this
それはこうやって回る
that's all
それで全部です
It seems to say that it is hiding behind you, so don't dig it.
後ろに隠れているから掘るなと言っているようです。
You haven't read it, right?
読んだことないですよね？
but someone has seen
でも誰かが見た
This is a new jigsaw puzzle
これは新しいジグソーパズルです
The back looks like this
背面はこんな感じです
I'll come back later
また来ます
why doesn't he let you see
なぜ彼はあなたに見せてくれないのですか
not him
彼ではありません
He looks like this on the back
後ろ姿はこんな感じです
Actually you just look at this
実はこれを見ているだけで
you can see the front
前が見えます
let's face it
それに直面しよう
This is called the back
これを裏といいます
English is called near sides
英語ではニアサイドと言います
near face and far side
近い側と遠い側
the far side
向こう側
In fact, you have already seen this
実際、あなたはすでにこれを見ました
It's different, right?
それは違いますよね？
There are many reasons behind this
これには多くの理由があります
The moon is billions of years old
月の年齢は数十億年です
in this career
このキャリアの中で
These rear impact craters
これらの後部衝突クレーター
It's the impact crater for food.
食べ物の衝突クレーターです。
are still well preserved
今でもよく保存されています
front of earth
地球正面
This side of the crater
クレーターのこちら側
Many are called by this black
多くの人がこの黒人に呼ばれます
In fact, volcanic rumors
実は火山の噂
almost covered
ほぼカバーされている
why is this
どうしてこれなの
this is another question
これは別の質問です
this is
これは
There are different theories trying to explain it
それを説明しようとするさまざまな理論があります
But at least we see that's the case
しかし、少なくともそれが事実であることがわかります
everyone has seen this
誰もがこれを見ました
How many people have seen this?
これを見た人は何人いますか？
There should be 21 people who have seen it
見た人は21人いるはず
Why did 21 people see who
なぜ21人が誰を見たのか
These people are collectively called Apollo workers.
これらの人々は総称してアポロ作業員と呼ばれます。
Because really 1969 all the way to 1972
だって実際には1969年から1972年までずっと
The American moon landing program is called the Apollo program
アメリカの月面着陸計画はアポロ計画と呼ばれています
do you all know
皆さんは知っていますか
A total of 7 times
計7回
3 people each time
各回3名様
7 times succeeded 6 times
7回 6回成功
The so-called success is later
いわゆる成功は後から
2 out of 3 people land on the moon
3人に2人が月に着陸
like walking on it
その上を歩くような
then pick it up
それからそれを拾う
6 successes
6回成功
In other words, 12 people walked on the moon
つまり、12人が月面を歩いたということになる
21 people all flew to the moon
21人全員で月へ飛んだ
flew from behind
後ろから飛んできた
he saw it with his own eyes
彼はそれを自分の目で見た
This is one of the princes
これは王子の一人です
take a picture of him and show us
彼の写真を撮って私たちに見せてください
I said seven times
7回言いました
only succeeded six times
6回しか成功しなかった
what happened again
また何が起こったのか
That's Apollo 13
それがアポロ13号です
A total of seven times from the 11th to the 17th
11日から17日まで全7回
No. 13 didn't work out
13番はうまくいかなかった
you may remember
覚えているかもしれません
have filmed
撮影しました
It's called the Apollo 13 movie.
それはアポロ13号と呼ばれる映画です。
great worth seeing
見る価値あり
He just failed to land on the moon
彼は月面着陸に失敗しただけだ
but he also flew
でも彼も飛んだ
fly behind to go around
後ろに飛んで回り込む
rounded the moon
月を丸めた
In the temporary that oxygen level exploded
酸素濃度が爆発した瞬間に
he can't go on
彼は続けられない
very delicate
とても繊細な
let him bring him back successfully
彼を無事に連れ戻してあげましょう
so that time was
だからあの時は
still lucky
まだ幸運です
let's go back to this one
これに戻りましょう
why doesn't he let you look behind
なぜ彼はあなたに後ろを見させてくれないのですか
This is still the two pictures just now
これはまだ今の2枚の写真です
this is special
これは特別です
this is
これは
Of course this color is painted by man
もちろんこの色は人間が描いたものです
His painting shows that
彼の絵はそれを示しています
The third highest and the deep valley
三番目に高い、深い谷
high and low terrain
高い地形も低い地形もある
moon shape
月形
OK
OK
the thing I just talked about
私が今話したこと
In fact, such a thing
実はそんなことも
you see him the same
あなたも彼を同じように見ています
To describe it is
それを説明すると、
he has a rotation period
彼にはローテーション期間がある
exactly the same as the revolution period
まさに革命期と同じ
let's say seven days
7日間としましょう
no matter how many days
何日でも
he is the same
彼も同じです
what does it mean
どういう意味ですか
when he is circling
彼が旋回しているとき
He only has one face facing the words
彼は言葉に対して一つの顔しか持っていない
when he makes a full circle
彼が一周するとき
He turned around by himself
彼は自分で振り向いた
did you notice
気づきましたか
he like this
彼はこれが好きです
is the public transfer circle
公共譲渡サークルです
At the same time, this time is the full circle of self-transfer
同時に、今回は自己転移の完全な循環です
these two cycles
この2つのサイクル
exactly the same time
全く同じ時間に
For us, for people on earth
私たちのため、地球上の人々のために
it is a facing earth
それは向かい合った地球です
this hasn't said why
これは理由を言っていない
just to tell you
ただあなたに伝えるために
Just described the same phenomenon again
同じ現象をもう一度説明しました
So my question is
それで私の質問は
Is this a coincidence
これは偶然ですか
how could it be such a coincidence
どうしてそんな偶然が起こるのでしょうか
Of course it's not a coincidence
もちろん偶然ではありません
for example
例えば
the moon to the earth
月から地球へ
if this is jupiter
これが木星なら
jupiter has a bunch of moons
木星には衛星がたくさんある
Jupiter has now been calculated to have sixty moons
木星には現在60個の衛星があると計算されている
a few of them are larger
より大きなもののいくつか
It's something we've known since the days of Homeoire
それはホメオワールの時代から私たちが知っていることです
all those moons are like this
それらの月はすべてこんな感じです
it's all like this
全部こんな感じです
no matter how close
どんなに近くても
Far
遠的
it's all like this
全部こんな感じです
don't let you look behind
後ろを見させないでください
so it's no coincidence
だからそれは偶然ではない
there must be some reason
何か理由があるはずだ
of course not
もちろん違います
not when gods created the world
神が世界を創造したときではない
he likes it
彼はそれが好き
of course not
もちろん違います
but
しかし
what is the reason
理由は何ですか
Here is a very simple diagram
これは非常に単純な図です
But I know I can't go too deep into it
でも、あまり深く踏み込むことはできないことは分かっている
But roughly, let me describe to you
しかし、大まかに説明しましょう
The reason behind this is called North Korean friction
その背後にある理由は北朝鮮摩擦と呼ばれています
There are North Korea and friction
北朝鮮と摩擦がある
it will end up like this
このようになります
and tell you a story
そしてあなたに物語を語ってください
That
それか
The so-called DPRK friction can be described like this
いわゆる北朝鮮摩擦は次のように説明できます。
This is our earth this green
これが私たちの地球、この緑です
This is the middle point is the North Pole
ここが北極点の中間点です
look like this
このように見える
let's see from above
上から見てみましょう
we see it this way
私たちはそれをこのように見ています
isn't the earth spinning
地球は回っているんじゃないの
The earth rotates like this
地球はこうやって回っている
is the farther one is farther away
遠いほど遠いです
Normally you can imagine saying
通常、次のように言うことが想像できます。
It would be great if this blue was sea water
この青が海水なら
you think of it as sea water
あなたはそれを海水だと思っていますか
Normally you would want to say
普通はこう言いたくなるだろう
the moon is here
月はここにあります
So the water is sucked up
それで水が吸い取られる
yes
はい
when the moon works
月が働くとき
The sea should have a high tide
海は満潮になるはずです
On the other side it will actually rise up
反対側では実際に上昇します
This place is actually far from the moon
実はこの場所は月から遠いのです
farthest place
一番遠い場所
How could it also go out high?
どうしてそれも高く出るのでしょうか？
This is because of centrifugal force
これは遠心力のせいです
I won't go into it in particular.
特に立ち入りません。
It's sharp and centrifugal
切れ味と遠心力がある
When the two balance
両者のバランスが取れたとき
we just one day
私たちはある日だけ
there will be two tidal bulges
潮汐隆起が2つあるでしょう
Do you see what this bulge means?
この膨らみが何を意味するかわかりますか？
you are the one who lives on earth
あなたは地球に住んでいる人です
You follow the earth around once a day
あなたは一日一回地球を追いかけます
the moon is here
月はここにあります
When you follow the moon to this place
月を追ってこの場所へ来ると
you'll find this place is now orgasm
この場所が今オーガズムに達していることがわかるだろう
highest water level
水位最高
you keep turning
あなたは向きを変え続ける
half a day later you transferred here
半日後、あなたはここに転送されました
You found the water dripping down here again
またここに水が滴っているのを見つけたね
Then it's high again
そしたらまた高いよ
That is to say, the tide creek rises and falls twice a day
つまり、潮の流れは1日に2回上がったり下がったりするのです。
because you are turning
あなたが向いているから
But actually the moon is also slightly within the day
でも実は月もわずかに日の中にあります
also moved a little
も少し動きました
So it's not exactly twice a day
つまり、1日に2回というわけではありません
a little over twice a day
1日2回強
that time is
その時は
In terms of this phenomenon
この現象に関して言えば
In fact, it will happen twice in 24 hours, 0510 minutes
実際には、24 時間 05 時 10 分に 2 回発生します。
Just once every 12 hours and 05 minutes
12時間05分に1回だけ
This is the Chaoxi that we normally know.
これが私たちが普段知っている潮渓です。
Of course there are some other
もちろん他にもいくつかあります
tidal constellation of its cycle
周期の潮の星座
I think I won't talk about it here
ここでは話さないと思います
The most important thing about this is this
この件で最も重要なことはこれです
That means you go to the beach to see
それはあなたがビーチに行って見ることを意味します
you sit there longer
あなたはそこにもっと長く座っています
sit for a long time
長時間座る
you will see the ebb and flow
満ち引きが見えるだろう
you can see twice
二度見できる
this is ideal
これは理想的です
but it's not
しかしそうではありません
actually kind of weird
実際にはちょっと変です
in fact you are not
実際、あなたはそうではありません
these two blue bumps
この2つの青い隆起
is attracted to the moon
月に惹かれます
fixed this direction
この方向を修正しました
But the earth must rotate underneath
でも地球はその下で回転しているはずだ
isn't the earth spinning
地球は回っているんじゃないの
it must turn
それは変わらなければなりません
There's friction here
ここに摩擦がある
This picture is also fun
この写真も面白いですね
This picture is from the Internet when I leaked it
この写真はネット上から流出したものです
This color is not what I ordered
この色は私が注文したものではありません
But when I talk to students
しかし、生徒たちと話していると、
I suddenly found out
突然知りました
I'm describing blue, green, friction
青、緑、摩擦について説明しています
it's wired
有線です
people have friction
人々には摩擦がある
when rubbing
こするとき
You see you are speaking to the earth
あなたは地球に話しかけているのがわかります
Since there is friction
摩擦があるので
He wants to drag him away
彼は彼を引きずり去ろうとしている
He pulled him more and more
彼はますます彼を引っ張った
He tried to pull him away again
彼は再び彼を引き離そうとした
The result is a little bit like a slant
結果は少し斜めになった感じです
It doesn't matter if it's slanted or not
傾いてるかどうかは関係ない
anyway there is friction
とにかく摩擦がある
When there is friction, you know that energy is being consumed
摩擦があるとエネルギーが消費されることが分かります
In fact we have many of these
実際、私たちはこれらをたくさん持っています
The idea is to say
アイデアはこう言うことです
use tidal power
潮力を利用する
In fact, the principle of tidal power generation
実は潮力発電の原理は、
actually
実際
Turn this friction directly into heat energy
この摩擦を直接熱エネルギーに変える
Go through our phone first
まずは電話をご利用ください
use up
使い切る
finally become hot
やっと熱くなった
Let's use it in the middle
途中で使いましょう
that's where this energy comes from
それがこのエネルギーの源です
In terms of the earth
地球でいえば
turn out
消す
Slower and slower
どんどん遅くなる
always look like this
いつもこんな感じ
These two are there like brake pads
この2つはブレーキパッドのようにそこにあります
I'm at the bottom, I insist on turning
私は最下位にいる、私は向きを変えることを主張する
Isn't that getting slower and slower?
どんどん遅くなっていませんか？
so
それで
Judging by this phenomenon
この現象から判断すると
First
初め
This is tidal friction
これが潮汐摩擦です
It causes a phenomenon called
と呼ばれる現象を引き起こします。
The earth is turning slower and slower
地球の回転はますます遅くなっている
this
これ
you don't know right
あなたは正しく知りません
yes
はい
your parents and children
あなたの両親と子供たち
Have your parents talked about it?
ご両親はそのことについて話しましたか？
days are getting harder
日が厳しくなってきています
Do you have
ありますか
the days are getting longer really
本当に日が長くなってきました
how is the day
今日はどうですか
we are now 24 hours a day
私たちは今、1日24時間体制です
In fact, every day is different
実際、毎日は違います
long time watching
長い間見てる
Because of this tidal friction phenomenon
この潮汐摩擦現象により、
you say the number is small
あなたは数が少ないと言いました
I tell you
私はあなたに言います
I'll show you how small it is
どれだけ小さいか見せてあげるよ
today if say
今日言うなら
we are so long today
今日はとても長いです
a hundred years ago
百年前
Today should be a little shorter than now, right?
今日は今より少し短いはずですよね？
Aren't we turning slower and slower?
私たちの回転はますます遅くなっていませんか？
So that time will be a little shorter
その時間は少し短くなりますので
How short is it?
どのくらい短いですか？
Only a thousandth of a second short
わずか1000分の1秒短い
You say it's nothing
何もないって君は言う
that's all
それで全部です
do i just worry
私が心配しているだけですか？
will i know
分かりますか
you don't have to worry
心配する必要はありません
you won't know
あなたには分からないでしょう
But precision scientific instruments can measure
しかし、精密な科学機器は測定することができます。
so what
だから何
nothing wrong
何も間違っていません
ok let's continue the story
はい、話を続けましょう
Scientific instruments are boring anyway.
科学機器はとにかく退屈です。
Since I think the earth is turning slower and slower
地球の回転はどんどん遅くなっていると思うので
I can't measure it either
私も測れません
I can't go directly
直接行けない
not so accurate
あまり正確ではありません
A hundred years ago there were no good clocks
100年前には良い時計はありませんでした
what to do
何をすべきか
There are clever ways to find this kind of evidence
この種の証拠を見つける賢い方法があります
this is an interesting rumor
これは興味深い噂です
What about this story?
この話はどうでしょうか？
For example, this is the earth
たとえば、これは地球です
If a certain time over the sun stone
サンストーンを一定時間越えると
We just saw that one of those dark shadows
私たちはちょうどその暗い影の一つを見たところです
If it is said that the sun power stone at that time
当時の太陽のパワーストーンと言えば
The trajectory is like this
軌跡はこんな感じ
That is to say, in this yellow belt
つまり、この黄色帯の中で
Everyone will see that day
誰もがその日を見るだろう
Sunstone looks like this
サンストーンはこんな感じ
This is a real event
これは実際の出来事です
This is an example of what I'm talking about
これは私が話していることの一例です
This example is
この例は
136 BC on a certain day
紀元前136年のある日
There should have been a Sunstone
サンストーンがあったはず
and there really are
そして本当にあります
Because this example is inside the records of Babylon
この例はバビロンの記録の中にあるからです
There was no pen and paper in Babylon
バビロンには紙とペンはなかった
And engraved on that clay tablet
そしてその粘土板に刻まれました
air pattern paper
エアパターンペーパー
found inside fire pipes
消火パイプの中で見つかった
It is recorded that this day
この日はこう記録されている
It really happened that day full time
それは本当にその日フルタイムで起こりました
And that's how it was seen in Babylon
そしてそれがバビロンで見られた方法です
it's his record so what
それは彼の記録だから何だ
then we are now saying
それから私たちは今こう言っています
I said scientists are so boring
科学者はとても退屈だと言いました
it will be fine
大丈夫だよ
That day has happened this day full time
あの日はこの日フルタイムで起こった
I now have a way to recover that full-time full-time moon
私は今、そのフルタイムの満月を取り戻す方法を持っています
because we now know the position of the moon to the sun
なぜなら、私たちは太陽に対する月の位置を知っているからです。
And I know how it turns
そして私はそれがどのように変わるかを知っています
i rewind time
私は時間を巻き戻します
Rewind over 2000 years
2000年を巻き戻す
use the computer to calculate
コンピューターを使って計算する
Just do the math
計算してみよう
Counting to that day more than 2000 years ago
2000年以上前のあの日から数えて
That day the real moon is between the earth and the sun
その日、本当の月は地球と太陽の間にあります
really full time
本当にフルタイム
but sorry
でもごめんなさい
Babylon can't see that day full time
バビロンはその日をフルタイムで見ることができない
The place to see should be here
見どころはここだろう
The barbies are here and they are tired
バービーたちはここにいます、そして彼らは疲れています
what will happen
何が起こるか
really full time
本当にフルタイム
But people who saw him said he was in the Babi people
しかし、彼を見た人々は、彼はバビ族だと言いました。
We now count back to the computer
私たちは今コンピューターに逆算します
impossible
不可能
what went wrong
何が悪かったのか
because when we arrive
なぜなら私たちが到着したとき
Use 24 hours a day to turn the earth back
1日24時間を使って地球を元に戻しましょう
But it's not really 24 hours a day
でも実際は1日24時間ではないんです
It used to turn faster
昔はもっと速かったよ
you have to follow that
あなたはそれに従わなければなりません
The length of the day that changes a little bit turns back
少しずつ変わる一日の長さが振り返る
When you turn to the day more than 2000 years ago
2000年以上前のあの日に目を向けると
really that strip goes through the barbies
本当にそのストリップはバービーを通過します
is so
そうだね
then we now
それから私たちは今
This seems to become
これはなりそうです
records of people at that time
当時の人々の記録
can be used by me now to do
今私が行うために使用できます
To make a proof is to say
証明をするということは、
It's true that the earth is turning slower and slower
地球の自転がますます遅くなっているのは本当だ
and slow down
そして減速してください
That level is really what I just said
そのレベルは本当に今言ったことです
That is from modern experience measurement.
それは現代の経験測定によるものです。
This is actually found in the historical records
これは実際に歴史的記録に残っています
Evidence that the Earth is growing slower
地球の成長が遅くなっている証拠
this is awesome
これはすごいです
there is one more strange thing
もう一つ奇妙なことがあります
What I just talked about is thousands of years old
私が今話したことは何千年も前のことです
Of course, the earth is not only a few thousand years
もちろん、地球は数千年だけではありません
Earth is 4.6 billion years old
地球の年齢は46億歳
Shouldn't it be turning faster earlier?
もっと早く回ればいいんじゃないの？
how do i... is there any way to know
どうすれば...知る方法はありますか
This is another interesting observation
これもまた興味深い観察です
here is an amplifier
ここにアンプがあります
Prototype mirror to see
見る試作ミラー
a coral it grows
成長するサンゴ
Are corals living things?
サンゴは生き物ですか？
animal president
動物の社長
This kind of coral can still be found
このようなサンゴは今でも見られます
you know how long it is
どのくらい長いか知っていますか
it is every day
それは毎日です
it will secrete a layer
層を分泌します
this skeleton
この骸骨
one lap a day
1日1周
but winter and summer
でも冬と夏
Secretion varies in width
分泌の幅が異なる
maybe the temperature is different
温度が違うのかもしれない
so it
それはそう
I don't know how much winter will be
冬がどれくらいになるか分からない
grow faster
より早く成長する
Or it will grow faster in summer
それとも夏になると成長が早くなるのですか
but
しかし
its
これは
grow out
成長する
between this day
この日の間に
Qualification to this is one year
資格は1年です
Qualifying to this is another year
出場資格はまた一年かかる
It's another year to qualify for this
資格を得るにはあと1年かかる
How many bars are there in the middle?
真ん中の棒は何本ありますか？
you can count
数えることができます
you are under the magnifying glass
あなたは虫眼鏡の下にいる
Counting under a circular mirror
円形の鏡の下で数える
you don't want to count
数えたくないですか
just ask your students
生徒たちに聞いてみてください
public reading birth number
パブリックリーディングの出生番号
inverse number
逆数
you will know
あなたは知るだろう
Eh
えー
how many days in a year
一年に何日
can't it
それはできません
this
これ
This is another example
これは別の例です
this is
これは
400 million years ago
4億年前
one
一個
painted rock specimens
畫石標本
There are many such specimens
そういう標本はたくさんあるよ
different ages
さまざまな年齢
I only ality
私だけの存在
Let me show you, 400 million years ago, this is very recent
見せましょう、4億年前、これはごく最近のことです
Because the earth is 4.6 billion years old
地球の年齢は46億年だから
This is only less than one-tenth of the recent
これは最近の10分の1にも満たない。
four hundred million years
まだ4億年もある
The result of this subordinate is
この部下の結果は
At that time, there were about 400 days in a year
当時、1年は約400日でした
What does it mean?
どういう意味ですか？
We now have three hundred and sixty-five days in a year
現在、1年は365日です
At that time there were four hundred days in a year
当時、一年は四百日でした
What's the meaning?
どのような意味です？
This year, this will not change
今年もそれは変わらない
It's such a long journey, that's one year
とても長い旅だ、それは1年だ
that means
つまり
At that time, within a circle of the earth
その時、地球の円の中で
it spins four hundred times
それは400回回転します
Now it can only go around three hundred and sixty-five times
今では365回しか回らない
this is what it means
これがそれが意味するものです
That is to say, the rotation was faster at that time
つまり当時のほうが回転が速かったのです
Quite a lot, about 10% faster
ほぼ大幅に、約 10% 高速化されています
so you can, this is another
それでいいよ、これは別の
An evidence left to us by nature says
自然が私たちに残した証拠はこう言っています
Look, the earth is turning slower and slower
ほら、地球の回転はますます遅くなっている
it is true
それは本当です
this part
この部分
Just now the physical reason
今のところ物理的な理由
The evidence left by this earth
この地球が残した証拠
It's the same thing
それは同じことです
let's see again
もう一度見てみましょう
Well, this is good, the earth is turning slower and slower
まあ、これはいいことだ、地球の回転はますます遅くなっている
of course say it again
もちろんもう一度言います
You will never know in your life
人生で決して知ることはないだろう
too little difference
差が小さすぎる
But this is not the end of the matter
しかし、問題はこれで終わりではありません
You should know
あなたが知っておくべき
If the earth turns slower and slower
地球の回転がどんどん遅くなったら
If you ever read that physics mechanics
物理力学を読んだことがあれば
you may remember
覚えているかもしれません
There's a thing called conservation of foot momentum
足の運動量保存というものがある
this one thing it has
それが持っているのはこれだけです
There is a physical quantity called foot momentum
足の運動量という物理量がある
The bigger the momentum of the foot, the better the rotation
足の運動量が大きいほど回転が良くなります
The foot momentum is small and the rotation is slower
足の運動量が少なく回転が遅い
that thing
その事
that amount won't change
その額は変わらない
under the same circumstances
同じ状況下で
That is to say
つまり
Why is the earth spinning
なぜ地球は回っているのか
this is another question
これは別の質問です
students sometimes ask
生徒たちは時々尋ねます
Teacher, why does the earth rotate?
先生、地球はなぜ回るの？
why does it keep turning
なぜ回り続けるのか
Actually the answer is very simple
実は答えはとても簡単です
because it has so much foot momentum
足の勢いがすごいので
it can't be lost
それは失われることはありません
it just has to turn every day
毎日回せばいいだけ
foot momentum is conservative
足の勢いは控えめです
which means it won't increase
つまり増えない
will not become less
少なくなることはありません
now there is a problem
今問題があります
You say it turns slower and slower
回転がどんどん遅くなるって君は言う
less foot momentum
足の勢いが少なくなる
You said that the foot momentum is not much
足の勢いがあまりないって言ってたね
not less
それ以下ではない
where did it go
どこへ行ったのか
Where did the foot momentum go?
足の勢いはどこへ行ったのか？
this answer
この答え
foot momentum has run away
足の勢いが逃げてしまった
where did you go
あなたは何処に行きましたか？
the answer is
答えは
Who told me to slow down
誰が私にゆっくりするように言ったの
whoever has to take the momentum
誰が勢いをつかまなければならないのか
who made me slow down
誰が私を遅くさせたのか
moon
月
Pottery friction slows me down
陶器の摩擦で動きが鈍る
What about my angular momentum?
私の角運動量はどうなるでしょうか？
you have to mature you have to continue to take
成熟しなければならない、摂取し続けなければならない
how to take it is to use
それをどのように摂取するかは使用することです
Force drama, this is physics
フォースドラマ、これは物理学だ
what was the result
結果はどうなりましたか
The earth is spinning slower and slower
地球の自転はますます遅くなっている
Angular momentum is getting less and less
角運動量はどんどん小さくなっていきます
That angular momentum is indestructible
その角運動量は破壊できない
The angular momentum of the arm went to the moon
腕の角運動量は月へ行った
what about the moon
月はどうですか
That angular momentum is increasing
その角運動量は増加しています
As a result his reaction was
その結果、彼の反応はこうでした
he has to turn faster
彼はもっと早く回転しなければならない
Or he was revolving to
あるいは、彼は次のように回転していました
a little bigger
もう少し大きい
his final reaction
最後の彼の反応
turn out
消す
so
それで
It's not wrong that he's still orbiting the earth
彼がまだ地球の周りを回っているのは間違いではない
But he goes farther and farther
でも彼はどんどん遠くへ行ってしまう
sort of like a
のようなもの
go out like a spiral
螺旋のように出て行く
further and further
さらにさらにさらに
This one won't look too bad
これなら見た目も悪くないだろう
just slowly away
ただゆっくりと遠ざかっていくだけ
how many
幾つか
only so much a year
一年にほんのわずか
Click this much, about four centimeters, that's all.
これくらい、4センチくらいクリック、それだけです。
then this thing is true
それならこれは真実です
How dare I say it's true
それが本当だと言うことができますか
Because our mountain was cold
私たちの山は寒かったので
look how cool
見てください、なんてクールだろう
this is awesome
これはすごいです
Is this the face?
これが顔ですか？
There are now 1 2 3 4 5 on this moon
この月には今 1 2 3 4 5 があります
5 what have instruments placed on it
5 楽器が置かれているものは何ですか
Because at that time the Apollo program had boarded six times
当時、アポロ計画は6回も搭乗していたため、
Put a lot of weird instruments on it every time
毎回変な楽器をたくさん載せてます
besides
そのほか
two
二
There were other trips to the Soviet Union
他にもソ連への旅行はあった
No one in the Soviet Union has been there, yes
はい、誰もソ連に行ったことはありません
and unmanned lunar landers
そして無人月着陸船
logged in
ログインしました
Also let go of the instrument
楽器も手放す
There are a group of instrument people who look like this
こんな感じの楽器関係者の集団がいます
something like this
このようなもの
It is a special reflector
特殊な反射板です
It's a mirror, but it's the kind
鏡だけどそんなもの
at right angles to this
これと直角に
called
呼ばれた
Well, let's call it a reflector.
まあ、それを反射板と呼びましょう。
What is this for? What are you doing over there?
これは何のためにあるのですか?そこで何をしているのですか?
are we from earth
私たちは地球から来たのですか
wow this thing
うわー、これ
If I accidentally swing someone else
うっかり他人を振り回してしまったら
do we have it from earth
私たちは地球からそれを持っていますか
made a big telescope
大きな望遠鏡を作りました
the telescope probably
おそらく望遠鏡
At least one meter in diameter
少なくとも直径1メートル
be big enough
十分に大きくなる
just what
いったい何
Use a telescope to shoot lasers
望遠鏡を使ってレーザーを発射する
send laser
レーザーを送る
shot straight to the moon
月に向かってまっすぐに撃った
Then there are reflectors on the moon
それから月には鏡があります
it puts the mirror
それは鏡を置きます
That laser beam bounces back
そのレーザー光線は跳ね返る
This light, wow, hundreds of thousands of kilometers
この光、すごい、何十万キロも
send to receive back
送り返して受け取る
that time
その時
The amount of reflection is already very weak, very weak
反射の量はすでに非常に弱い、非常に弱い
this experiment is really bad
この実験は本当にひどいです
Do it well but do it successfully
うまくやるが成功する
what do you do
職業はなんですか
you are the time back in time
あなたは過去に戻った時間です
maybe a few seconds a few seconds
おそらく数秒、数秒
that can be measured very precisely
非常に正確に測定できる
Divide the speed of light by two
光速を2で割る
That's the distance
それが距離です
You measure this year and measure next year
今年も測定し、来年も測定する
Measure it next year, measure it if you have nothing to do
来年測ってみよう、何もすることがなかったら測ってみよう
measure ten years
10年を測る
You find it's getting farther and farther away
あなたはそれがどんどん遠ざかっていることに気づきます
Really, how much is it every year?
本当のところ、毎年いくらくらいなのでしょうか？
almost that much
ほぼそれくらい
Calculate this with us
私たちと一緒に計算してください
The formula of foot momentum and hand scale is the same
足の勢いと手のスケールの計算式は同じです
more and more far away from us
ますます私たちから遠ざかります
Every year almost so much now
今では毎年ほぼ同じくらい
so what
だから何
you can't see it, can you?
見えないですよね？
Did you see the volume getting smaller and smaller, no?
ボリュームがどんどん小さくなっているのがわかりましたか?
That's actually very little
それは実際にはごくわずかです
It seems that there is no need to worry, right?
心配する必要はないようですね？
not so good
あまりよくない
Look at our earth now
今私たちの地球を見てください
what about 100 years ago
100年前はどうだったのか
100 years ago this became 100
100年前はこれが100になった
All right
わかった
a little closer
もう少し近くに
Good 100 years I will give you 10,000 years
100年よかった、1万年あげよう
OK
OK
Do you think 10,000 years is not enough to win?
勝つには1万年では足りないと思いますか？
I give you 1 million years
あなたに100万年をあげます
Not enough for me to give you 100 million years
あなたに1億年を与えるのには十分ではありません
The earth is very old, no problem
地球はとても古い、問題ない
You are not enough to win in 100 million years
1億年後に勝つには君には足りない
I give you 1 billion years
10億年をあげます
you go admit it
あなたはそれを認めてください
billions of years ago
数十億年前
Wow
おお
where is the moon
月はどこですか
next to our earth
私たちの地球の隣に
what is it
それは何ですか
what does this mean
これは何を意味するのでしょうか
What is the moon next to the earth
地球の隣にある月は何ですか
What does that mean
どういう意味ですか
this
これ
It's not about digestion
消化の問題ではない
because it's true
それは本当だから
very important one
とても大切なもの
results of scientific research
科学研究の結果
research this thing
このことを研究してください
is the biggest look
最大の見た目です
The first person to study this phenomenon
この現象を最初に研究した人
more than a hundred years ago
百年以上前
call darwin
ダーウィンに電話してください
You say I know Darwin is the theory of evolution
あなたはダーウィンが進化論であることを知っていると言いました
not him
彼ではありません
is his son
彼の息子です
His son's name is Darwin, of course.
彼の息子の名前はもちろんダーウィンです。
The man who evolved was Charles Darwin
進化した男はチャールズ・ダーウィンだった
This astronomer's name is George Darwin
この天文学者の名前はジョージ・ダーウィンです
This is a famous astronomer
この人は有名な天文学者です
This is what he came up with
これが彼が思いついたものです
and calculated
そして計算された
We're all confirmed now
もう全員確定だよ
When he asked the question I just asked
彼が質問したとき、私はちょうど尋ねました
He boldly proposed a concept
彼は大胆にコンセプトを提案した
What does it mean when the moon was next to the earth?
月が地球の隣にあったということは何を意味するのでしょうか？
He said how the moon came
彼は月はどうやってできたのかと言いました
It was thrown by the earth spinning too fast
地球の回転が速すぎて投げられた
that's ok
それで大丈夫です
May I
いいですか
And you also know that the rotation is fast at that time
そしてその時の回転が速いことも分かります
right
右
Then it got slower and slower
それからどんどん遅くなった
as soon as the situation
状況が分かり次第
maybe in the event of some disturbance
おそらく何らかの混乱が生じた場合に
the whole piece ran away
作品全体が逃げ出した
The one that got away is our current moon
逃げたのは今の月
what's wrong
どうしたの
May I
いいですか
When this theory was proposed more than 100 years ago
この理論が100年以上前に提唱されたとき
immediately received a lot of attention
すぐに大きな注目を集めました
real
本物
Wow
おお
we understand now
私たちは今理解しました
and some even say
と言う人さえいます
you run away a piece
あなたは少し逃げます
The earth must be missing a piece
地球には欠片が欠けているに違いない
So isn't there a big pull?
それで大きな引力はないですか？
what is that pull
その引っ張りは何ですか
ocean
海洋
It's too cold, isn't it?
寒すぎますね。
look
見て
Wow
おお
this is great
これは素晴らしい
a theory like this
このような理論
The moon also understands
月も分かる
The ocean also understands
海もわかる
this is
これは
it's a real thing
それは本物です
OK
OK
so at that time
だからその時は
growth of the moon
月の成長
This Kangying, this George Darwin proposed
この康英、このジョージ・ダーウィンが提案した
It was proposed in 1878
1878年に提案されました
This theory is nicknamed this
この理論にはこんなあだ名が付けられています
Parenthood theory
親子理論と呼ばれる
It's parent-child talk
親子の話です
It means that the moon is the descendant of our earth.
それは月が地球の子孫であることを意味します。
This is you see my picture is so big and only write this small piece
これは私の写真がとても大きいので、この小さな部分だけを書いてください。
what is the reason
理由は何ですか
Because there's something underneath, right?
だって下に何かあるじゃないですか。
This is the theory number one of the birth of the moon
これが月誕生の第一の理論です
is there number two
2番はありますか
This is number one what I just said
これが今私が言ったことの1番です
It's like going to World University, right?
世界大学に行くようなものですよね？
Of course, some people think it's impossible.
もちろん、それは不可能だと思う人もいます。
but this
しかしこれは
not like that
あのようでなく
it was then
それはその時でした
When you formed, when the solar system formed, large and small gathered
あなたが形成されたとき、太陽系が形成されたとき、大小の人々が集まりました
I gather here
ここに集まります
Are you the moon or the earth?
あなたは月ですか、それとも地球ですか?
it's also a theory
それも理論です
there's nothing wrong with that
それは何も問題ありません
This is called, nicknamed "Siblings"
これを「兄弟」と呼びます。
called sisterhood
姉妹関係と呼ばれる
There's another piece over here
ここに別の作品があります
It's theory number two and number three.
それは理論その2とその3です。
number three is
3番目は
it's all modern
それはすべて現代的です
This was a hundred years ago, more than a hundred years ago
これは百年前のこと、百年以上前のこと
This is what the spouse said
配偶者はこう言いました
spouse said
配偶者が言いました
what is it then
それは何ですか
just look at it
それを見てください
was captured
捕らえられた
That is to say, our earth was a
つまり、私たちの地球は
bachelor
学士
I am professional
私はプロフェッショナルです
what year
何年
it's all about
それはすべてです
Early days of the solar system, infancy
太陽系の初期、幼少期
There won't be such a big change later
後はそこまで大きな変化はない
We accidentally walked a guy nearby
私たちは誤って近くの男を歩いてしまいました
is the moon
月です
got sucked into the earth
地球に吸い込まれてしまった
It's okay if there's nothing wrong with it
何も問題がなければ大丈夫です
This is theory number three
これが理論その3です
Every theory it supports what it says
あらゆる理論がそれを裏付けています
must be right in school
学校にいるはずだ
It's also possible that it's too impossible
無理すぎる可能性もある
But you just say
でもあなたはただこう言います
pei says
ペイは言う
We now think Mars has two small moons
現在、火星には小さな衛星が 2 つあると考えられています
I just had a photo
ちょうど写真があったので
That's how the two little moons were caught just now
たった今、二つの小さな月がそうやって捉えられたんだ
So this is not to say nonsense.
したがって、これはナンセンスと言っているわけではありません。
it's really possible
本当に可能です
Is it possible in school
学校でも可能ですか
Plus
プラス
At the time of this Lantern Moon
このランタンムーンの頃には
Every time some rocks come back
石が戻ってくるたびに
rocks of the moon moved back
月の石が後退した
Then draw in the laboratory
それから実験室で絵を描きます
compared with the earth
地球と比べて
It's basically the same as the rocks of the earth.
基本的には地球の岩石と同じです。
But there's always something a little different
でもいつも何かが少し違う
those little ones are different
それらの小さなものは違います
Can you use any of these theories to explain
これらの理論のいずれかを使用して説明できますか
The result is almost
結果はほぼ
Every theory seems to be right
どの理論も正しいように見える
There are also flaws
欠陥もあります
Then we can't argue, right?
それなら議論できないですよね？
Then we will write these three here now
それでは、この 3 つをここに書きます
You can also be your judge
あなたも裁判官になることができます
whichever one you like, right?
どっちでもいいですよね？
we wait for you to reveal
あなたが明らかにするのを待っています
because we now only think
私たちは今考えるだけだから
It can't be all right, right?
大丈夫というわけにはいかないですよね？
then you can now
それなら今すぐできます
You are the only one like this
こんな人はあなただけです
Then I will tell you the answer now
それでは今すぐ答えを教えます
the answer is
答えは
none of above
以上皆非
We now think the answer is
私たちは今、その答えは次のように考えています。
it came out
それが出てきた
Where did it come from?
それはどこから来たのか？
knocked out
ノックアウト
what is knocked out
何がノックアウトされたのか
this is still
これはまだです
this is not a photo
これは写真ではありません
This is of course human
これはもちろん人間です
This is also the infancy of the solar system
これは太陽系の初期でもあります
That is, within the first 100 million years of 4.6 billion years ago
つまり、46億年前から最初の1億年以内に
Isn't it infancy?
幼児期じゃないの？
something that happened at that time
その時に起こった何か
what does it look like
それは何に見えますか
It was at that time that things were still not in order
まだ事態が整っていない頃だった
It's just that the solar system is not messed up
太陽系が壊れてないだけ
everyone has everyone's track
誰もがみんなのトラックを持っています
But it hasn't been cleaned yet.
しかし、まだ掃除されていません。
once the earth collided with another guy
かつて地球が他の男と衝突したとき
that guy is big enough
あの人は十分大きいです
If the earth is so big
地球がそんなに大きいなら
That guy probably
あの人はきっと
he is so big
彼はとても大きいです
Mars is big enough
火星は十分大きい
These two things collided
この二つが衝突した
Of course it's not the same when we bump into each other
もちろんぶつかったら違うよ
hit it hard
強く打ってください
The whole thing just hits everything into ashes
すべてが灰になるだけだ
This bomb is everywhere
この爆弾はどこにでもあります
something knocked out
何かがノックアウトされた
Most of the things crashed out and flew all over the sky
ほとんどのものは衝突して空に飛び散った
Big back and sucked back
大きな背中と吸い込まれた背中
right? drop back again
そうでしょう？また戻ってください
still something to get
まだ何か得るものがある
Accidentally get more energy
偶然より多くのエネルギーを得る
run away, run away forever
逃げて、永遠に逃げて
there are many things
多くのものがあります
Didn't run away, didn't fall down
逃げなかった、転ばなかった
it had to go around
それは回らなければならなかった
because it also has foot momentum
足の勢いもあるので
If you have feet, you have to go around
足があるなら回らなければならない
It is likely that the earth at that time
おそらく当時の地球は
There is a ring
指輪があります
All are the fastest substances
すべては最速の物質です
like what it is now
今はどうなっているのか
rage star is like this
レイジスターはこんな感じ
not saturn
土星ではありません
Doesn't Saturn have rings?
土星には輪がないのですか？
I guess the earth was like that at that time
あの頃の地球もそうだったんだろうな
Then what
じゃあ何
inside the rings of saturn
土星の輪の内側で
these big and small things
これらの大きなことや小さなこと
It has this gravitational force in it
この重力が内部にあります
slowly inhale
ゆっくりと吸い込む
Doesn't it like to be round in the end?
結局丸いのが好きじゃないですか？
yes big enough
はい、十分な大きさです
If it is round enough, it will become the moon, that's not how it came about
丸ければ月になる そんなふうに生まれたわけじゃない
Is this theory over?
この理論は終わったのでしょうか？
People say it's right, right, right, right?
人々はそれが正しい、正しい、そう言うでしょう？
You want to prove it, how can such a person prove it?
あなたはそれを証明したいのですが、そのような人はどうやってそれを証明できますか？
It's right for you to talk nonsense like this.
こんなくだらない話をするのは正しいことだ。
But this is not nonsense now, it has been proven to be broken
しかし、これは今ではナンセンスではありません、それは壊れていることが証明されました
How was it confirmed?
どのように確認されましたか?
confirmed in the computer
コンピューターで確認した
this was ten years ago
これは10年前のことです
There are scientists who use computers
科学者はコンピューターを使用します
The computer is getting bigger and bigger, the ability, this ability
コンピューターはどんどん大きくなっていきます、その能力、この能力
more and more powerful
ますます強力になる
I am not me, I say scientists
私は私ではありません、科学者だと言います
such a crash event
そんな衝突事件
Simulate, use a computer to simulate
シミュレートする、コンピューターを使用してシミュレートする
Mock doesn't tell him to call someone to draw Kao Dong Tu
モックはカオ・ドン・トゥを描くために誰かを呼ぶようにとは言いません
Then draw it like this
じゃあこんな感じに描きます
No, let him do the math
いいえ、彼に計算させましょう
He must base his calculations on
彼は次のような計算に基づいていなければなりません
correct physics
正しい物理学
because it's not easy
それは簡単ではないから
All relevant physical aspects of such events
このようなイベントに関連するすべての物理的側面
All truths must be written in mathematical formulas
すべての真実は数式で記述されなければなりません
Then give him a two thing and start him banging
それから彼に 2 つのことを与えて、彼を叩き始めます
After hitting it, it will become like this
叩くとこうなります
then what happens
それで何が起こるか
Look at the last in the computer
最後をパソコンで見てください
Is it possible to create a moon
月を作ることは可能ですか
this thing worked
これはうまくいきました
Since it was successful
成功したので
Is there anyone going to steal something?
何かを盗もうとする人はいますか？
really can be successful
本当に成功できる
So the theory is accepted
だからその理論は受け入れられる
This theory was accepted
この理論は受け入れられた
as we now think
私たちが今考えているように
That's how the moon came about
月はこうして生まれた
that's how it came out
こんな感じで出てきました
Of course, there are many other problems derived from this.
もちろん、このことから他にも多くの問題が派生します。
For example, maybe you see this and you think
たとえば、これを見てこう思うかもしれません。
Yes, that Jupiter
そう、あの木星です
Isn't Saturn just like this now?
土星も今まさにこんな感じではないでしょうか？
Then you can ask the next sentence saying
次に、次の文を尋ねることができます。
those Saturn things
それらの土星のもの
Instead, why didn't it grow into a moon?
逆に、なぜ月に成長しなかったのでしょうか？
why not
なぜだめですか
Why can the earth grow into the moon
なぜ地球は月まで成長できるのか
I know this too
これは私も知っています
know why
理由を知っている
Because Saturn is bigger
土星の方が大きいから
that gravity is very strong
重力がとても強いということ
the substance near it
その近くにある物質
want to attract each other
お互いを引き寄せたい
want to be the moon
月になりたい
It cannot be done in the process of a proto-moon
原始月の過程ではそれはできません
Because the tidal force is too strong
潮汐力が強すぎるので
If you want to mess with that layer, I'll tear it up
その層をいじりたいなら、引き裂いてやる
tidal force will tear it apart
潮汐力で引き裂かれるだろう
so it doesn't fit
だから合わない
I know this too
これは私も知っています
the earth is so small
地球はとても小さい
The tidal force is not so fierce
潮汐力はそれほど激しくない
it is possible to grow a moon
月を成長させることは可能です
this is also possible
これも可能です
what about this theory
この理論はどうですか
by the way
ところで
some get some unexpected benefits
予期せぬ恩恵を受ける人もいます
For example, I just said
たとえば、先ほど言いました
stones you brought from karma
あなたがカルマから持ってきた石
i'll say something
何か言います
How is it different from the earth
地球とどう違うの？
then use this theory
次にこの理論を使用します
Can you explain those differences?
それらの違いを説明してもらえますか？
it's not my specialty
それは私の専門ではありません
but the answer is yes
しかし答えはイエスです
there are some interesting
いくつか興味深いものがあります
conscious
意識的
for example by-products
例えば副産物など
Here I will tell one of them is very interesting
ここで、そのうちの1つが非常に興味深いものであることをお話します
this thing is like this
これはこんな感じです
This is in our solar system
これは私たちの太陽系にあります
I say the tuba members of the family
チューバ族のメンバーって言うんです
This size is the proportion is correct
このサイズは比率が正しいです
If the earth is so big
地球がそんなに大きいなら
There are four older than us
私たちより年上の人が4人います
Just the four outside
外には4人だけ
the outer four
外側の4つ
The biggest is of course Jupiter
一番大きいのはもちろん木星です
then saturn
それから土星
Uranus Kaiwang
天王星 凱王星
There is also a name that was removed from the list a few years ago
数年前にリストから外された名前もある
The heart is small, don't worry about it
心は小さい、心配しないでください
The earth is actually only this big
地球って本当はこれくらいしかないんだよ
look at this
これを見てください
this is our planet
ここは私たちの惑星です
this is ours
これは私たちのものです
this is still our planet
ここはまだ私たちの惑星です
This is us, this is what's inside us
これが私たち、これが私たちの内側にあるものです
One is Jingxing
一人はジンシンです
about the same size , a little bit smaller than us
ほぼ同じサイズですが、私たちより少し小さいです
It doesn't matter, the living star is just that big
関係ないよ、生きている星はそれだけ大きいんだ
these are all the moons
これらはすべて月です
bigger moon
より大きな月
How big is that small moon?
その小さな月はどれくらいの大きさですか？
There are hundreds of them
何百もある
this is big
これは大きいです
a whole bunch of these planets
これらの惑星がたくさん
family of the moon
月の家族
members line up
メンバーが並ぶ
from largest to second largest
最大から 2 番目に大きいものまで
the moon is here
月はここにあります
this one
これです
these four
この4つ
is famous
有名です
called galilean moon
ガリラヤの月と呼ばれる
It's all about Jupiter
それはすべて木星についてです
Galileo
ガリレオ
not binoculars
双眼鏡ではありません
time to see it ? also see jupiter
それを見る時が来ましたか? 木星も見ましょう
As a result, I saw four moons, these four
その結果、4つの月が見えました、この4つは
is large
は大きい
OK look
わかりました、見てください
The moon, all the moons line up like this
月 月が全部こうやって並んでる
our moon is really big
私たちの月は本当に大きいです
Although not the biggest
最大ではありませんが、
but it's really big
でも本当に大きいです
how about this
これはどう
look back
振り返って
so big
とても大きく
its the moon
それは月です
we do
私たちはそうします
our moon
私たちの月
How did we get such a big moon
どうやってあんな大きな月ができたんだろう
our moon is really big
私たちの月は本当に大きいです
I kid you not
冗談じゃないよ
in the end is
結局のところは
This has always been a problem
これは常に問題でした
Astronomers have been asking this question too
天文学者もこの疑問を抱いています
Why is our moon so big?
私たちの月はなぜあんなに大きいのでしょうか?
have no idea
全く分かりません
Now
現在
Now is this a problem? How big does it grow?
これは問題ですか? どれくらい大きくなるでしょうか?
How old is it?
これはどれくらい古いのですか？
it can even be
それさえありえます
The one bigger than our earth is fine.
地球より大きいものでも大丈夫です。
that is to say we are now
つまり私たちは今いるのです
we live on the small one
私たちは小さなもので生きています
those hearts
それらの心
why does it have to be so much smaller than you
なぜあなたよりずっと小さい必要があるのですか
No one stipulated this
誰もこれを規定しなかった
Whatever happens when it hits
当たったら何が起こっても
it's big or small
それは大きいか小さいか
So what if it's quite big now?
それで、それが今かなり大きくなったらどうなるでしょうか？
no problem, right?
問題ないですよね？
Ok, this problem is also solved
よし、この問題も解決だ
I believe this question is for us
この質問は私たちへの質問だと思います
In fact, very few people actually ask this question.
実際、この質問をする人はほとんどいません。
right
右
Because we have long been used to our moon
私たちは長い間月に慣れているから
I thought the moon in the world should be this big
世界の月はこれくらい大きくあるべきだと思った
No la
いやラ
OK
OK
Another astronomer or physicist
別の天文学者または物理学者
Anyway, the puzzling thing is this
とにかく、不可解なのはこれです
You see, the earth is placed like this
ほら、地球はこうやって配置されているんです
then you call
それからあなたは電話します
So you buy it back and buy it like this
だからあなたはそれを買い戻して、このようにそれを買うのです
It's not that you shake it when you buy it.
買うときに振るわけではありません。
It's like this when I bought it.
買った時はこんな感じ。
I didn't move it
動かさなかった
right
右
We all... all one-ball hawks do this, right?
私たち全員…ワンボールタカ派はみんなこれをやりますよね？
Why
なぜ
Doesn't it look good?
見た目が良くありませんか？
it's slanted
傾いています
What is it oblique to?
何に対して斜めになっているのでしょうか？
that's right
それは正しい
Then we now call it yellow rice noodles
それから私たちはそれを黄色いビーフンと呼びます
is the sun
太陽です
we know which side of the sun
私たちは太陽のどちら側かを知っています
If the face is flat
顔が平らな場合
Our earth actually rotates in Y direction
私たちの地球は実際には Y 方向に回転しています
Then there's an angle here, right?
そうすると、ここに角度がありますよね？
This is called the inclination of the Earth's rotation.
これを地球の自転の傾きといいます。
The angle of 23 and a half degrees
角度は23度半
It is because of this angle that 4G is available, right?
この角度だからこそ4Gが使えるのですね。
think about it
考えてみてください
If it turns like this
こうなったら
until the sun turns like this
太陽がこうなるまで
There is no 4G here
ここには4Gはありません
4G too
4Gも
We figured it out after we knew there were these things
こういうものがあると知ってから、私たちはそれを理解しました
Yes, that's right
はい、そうです
That's how it came
それでこうなった
why is it so crooked
なぜこんなに曲がっているのか
because of you because
あなたのせいで
According to the theory of our solar system formation
私たちの太陽系形成理論によると
is generated like this
このように生成されます
4.6 billion years ago
46億年前
a big pot
大きな鍋
a lot of little things
たくさんの小さなこと
everyone is here
みんながここにいます
everyone is going around
みんなが回っている
why turn
なぜ向きを変えるのか
because when it is generated
なぜならそれが生成されるとき
accidentally assigned a lot of angular momentum
誤って多くの角運動量を割り当ててしまう
what about it
それはどうですか
had to go around
回らなければならなかった
just turn
ただ回してください
when turning
曲がるとき
under gravity
重力の下で
This is how my tour is already
私のツアーはすでにこんな感じです
The most stable condition is a flat turn
一番安定するのはフラットターンです
a disc turn
ディスクの回転
So the early solar system
つまり初期の太陽系は
It's such a big pile of material
とても大きな資料の山です
another plate
別の皿
These things start with each other
これらのことはお互いから始まります
It starts to generate planets due to spiritual power
霊力により惑星を生成し始める
little parade what moon
小さなパレード何月
so formed
そう形成された
you pay attention when forming
形成するときに注意します
Every thing that forms is assigned some angle measure
形成されるすべてのものには、何らかの角度の尺度が割り当てられます
it's going to turn like this
このように変わります
so these planets
だからこれらの惑星は
on this face
この顔に
Everything turns like this
すべてがこうなる
This is how the revolution works
革命はこうやって起こる
small circle like this
このような小さなサークル
big circle like this
このような大きな円
Anyway, it's like this
とにかく、こんな感じです
It rotates like this
こんな感じで回転します
also in the same direction
それも同じ方向に
Because it's divided into such an angular measure
こんな角度で区切られているので
what about it
それはどうですか
it just gets better
それはただ良くなります
Just this sentence
この一文だけ
so it turns like this
だからこうなる
That's a straight turn
それは直角です
Why is it crooked?
なぜ曲がっているのですか？
why is it crooked
なぜ曲がっているのか
Whether it will be crooked or not
曲がるかどうか
Because the angle it is assigned is a small vector
割り当てられた角度は小さなベクトルであるため、
It's really the angle
まさに角度ですね
It's all written down now
もう全部書き終わった
It's pretty well written.
かなりよく書かれています。
this has always been a problem
これは常に問題でした
so why
なぜ
will slant off
傾いてしまいます
Then you look at other planets found
次に、見つかった他の惑星を見てみましょう
Mars is crooked too
火星も曲がってるよ
Mars is about the same as us
火星は私たちとほぼ同じです
Still more than 20 degrees crooked
まだ20度以上曲がってます
Well
良い
other planets
他の惑星
less crooked
比較不歪
there is an even stranger
さらに見知らぬ人がいます
In fact, it is careful
実は慎重ですよ
it's not crooked
曲がっていません
But it turns like this
でもこうなります
turn instead
代わりに向きを変える
it turns very slowly
とてもゆっくりと回転します
but the opposite
しかしその反対
it's even weirder
それはさらに奇妙です
I don't know why
どうしてか分かりません
It can't be reversed.
それを元に戻すことはできません。
That is to say, you carefully
つまり、慎重に
The sun comes out from the west
太陽が西から出てくる
real
本物
That is to say, these rotations of these planets
つまり、これらの惑星の回転は
Why is it so strange
なぜそんなに奇妙なのでしょうか
The simplest is why our earth is so crooked
最も単純なのは、なぜ私たちの地球はこんなに曲がっているのかということです
Well, it seems that I can answer it now.
さて、これで答えられるようです。
It's just crooked
ただ曲がってるだけだよ
Didn't you get hit before?
前にも殴られませんでしたか？
hit it
それを打つ
If the shoe is bumped, it will be crooked.
靴がぶつかると曲がってしまいます。
that's all
それで全部です
how big is that
それはどれくらい大きいですか
what a powerful one
なんて強力なのだろう
How can this collider bend so much?
この衝突型加速器はどのようにしてこれほど曲がることができるのでしょうか?
It seems that this thing is not working
どうやらこれは機能していないようです
this is not enough
これはたりない
possibly earlier
おそらくもっと早く
when there is a larger combination
より大きな組み合わせがある場合
Big and small
大小
It's crooked when it's messed up
めちゃくちゃになると曲がってしまう
that other
そのほかの
The core can also be explained like this
核心は次のようにも説明できます
Why does carefulness reverse
なぜ慎重さが逆転するのか
obviously got hit
明らかに殴られた
reverse
逆行
Will it be reversed?
逆になるのでしょうか？
that's all
それで全部です
this is all
これですべてです
ever-great problem
永遠の大きな問題
But now we put this
しかし今、私たちはこれを置きます
big collider this
ビッグコライダーこれ
concept brought in
持ち込まれたコンセプト
seems to be able to explain
説明できるようです
OK, this is what we are talking about about the moon
OK、これが月について話していることです
deep
深層
we again
私たちはまた
It also announced and advertised some human exploration of the moon
また、有人による月探査についても発表および宣伝しました。
also a story
物語でもある
we tell stories like this
私たちはこのような話をします
What I just said has nothing to do with people
私が今言ったことは人々には関係ありません
Except those recorded at the time of the date
日付時点で記録されているものに加えて、
Everything else is natural
それ以外はすべて自然です
It's just that people have a special love for the moon
人は月に対して特別な愛情を持っているというだけです
did a lot of things
たくさんのことをした
This story can be told from 1958 to 1957
この物語は 1958 年から 1957 年にかけて語られます。
this day october 4th
この日10月4日
It's the day humans enter the space age
人類が宇宙時代に突入する日です
what happened
どうしたの
the Soviet Union
ソビエト連邦
this country no longer exists
この国はもう存在しない
The Soviet Union launched an artificial miniature
ソ連が人工ミニチュアを打ち上げた
into orbit
軌道へ
this is a big deal
これは大変なことだ
because it's too hard
難しすぎるから
Now we find it easy to do
今ではそれが簡単にできるようになりました
it's really hard to do
それは本当に難しいです
This is the first round in the middle of the cold war
冷戦真っ只中の第一ラウンド
It's the camp of the Soviet Union
ここはソ連のキャンプだ
he was the first to enter the orbit of a satellite
彼は人工衛星の軌道に入った最初の人だった
first his artificial satellite into orbit
彼の人工衛星が初めて軌道に乗りました
Satellite called Sparknik 1
スパークニク1号と呼ばれる衛星
This is a photo of a replica
これはレプリカの写真です
not so big
それほど大きくない
probably only this big
おそらくこれくらいの大きさしかない
this is rough
これはひどいです
You look like a child's toy now
もう子供のおもちゃみたいだね
He went into orbit and did nothing
彼は軌道に乗って何もしなかった
It is to play the signal BVV of a tape recorder
テープレコーダーのBVV信号を再生します
That's it
それでおしまい
The ground received that signal
地上がその信号を受信した
Wow, this is a great progress for mankind
うわー、これは人類にとって大きな進歩です
great advance in civilization
文明の大きな進歩
just at that moment
就那一瞬間
This is humanity entering the space age
これが人類の宇宙時代への突入です
the back of this
これの裏側
lots of questions to ask
たくさんの質問
soviet won
ソビエトウォン
This fact is
この事実は、
is history
歴史です
Simply put
簡単に言えば
that time
その時
want to enter satellite
衛星に入りたい
to get into orbit
軌道に乗るために
you must have powerful rockets
強力なロケットを持っている必要があります
Where was the mighty rocket at that time
当時の強力なロケットはどこにありましたか
in Germany
ドイツ語に
How can there be in Germany?
どうしてドイツにそんなことがあり得るのでしょうか？
because he fought
彼は戦ったから
When he developed during the 20th World War
彼が第二次世界大戦中に成長したとき
Called the V2 rocket
V2ロケットと呼ばれる
I don't know the detailed story here.
ここの詳しい話は分かりません。
not too detailed
不講太詳細
this is a big war
これは大きな戦争だ
at the end
最後に
used by germany to bomb london
ドイツがロンドン爆撃に使用
Britain was bombed badly
イギリスはひどい爆撃を受けた
But soon the war will be over
でももうすぐ戦争は終わる
when it's over
それが終わったら
within a few months
数か月以内に
cold war has begun
冷戦が始まった
the first to enter berlin
最初にベルリンに入った人
soviet red army
ソ連赤軍
Once the Soviet Union entered the Red Army and entered Germany,
ソ連が赤軍に入りドイツに侵攻すると、
all good things
いいこと
Already spotted
すでに発見されています
block all
全部封鎖
move all back to germany
全員をドイツに戻す
Go to the Soviet Union, the rocket power is the most important one
ソ連に行こう、ロケットパワーが最も重要だ
personnel data equipment
人事データ機器
All the knowledge is packaged and sent back to the Soviet Union
すべての知識はパッケージ化されてソ連に送り返される
So later, it entered the humane world and was already in orbit.
それでその後、それは人間の世界に入り、すでに軌道上にありました。
This rocket won't work. It's too small. It needs to be bigger and bigger.
このロケットはうまくいきません。小さすぎます。もっと大きくする必要があります。
But no matter what, the Soviet Union has this advantage
しかし、何があろうとも、ソ連にはこの利点があります
first in orbit
最初に軌道上にある
This is the first round of the Cold War, the Soviet Union has already won
これは冷戦の第一ラウンドであり、ソ連はすでに勝利している
America lost, but not too much
アメリカは負けたが、それほど大きくはなかった
Because you see this January of the second year
この2年目の1月を見ているから
America also succeeded
アメリカも成功した
Also successfully launched his first artificial satellite
初の人工衛星の打ち上げにも成功
this photo is very famous
この写真はとても有名です
A photo of a celebration dinner at the White House
ホワイトハウスでの祝賀ディナーの写真
this is not a rocket
これはロケットではありません
rocket big big big big
ロケットビッグビッグビッグビッグ
This is the artificial satellite on top of the rocket
これはロケットの上にある人工衛星です
This is what artificial satellites look like
人工衛星はこんな感じ
there is an instrument inside
中に楽器があります
It is the instrument used by this professor
それはこの教授が使っている楽器です
It's called Van Allen
ヴァン・アレンといいます
Have any students heard
聞いた学生はいますか
Pan Allan radiation belts outside the Earth
地球外のパンアラン放射線帯
It's made in his laboratory
それは彼の研究室で作られています
of these three
この3つのうちの
This was an official at the time
この人は当時の公務員だった
officials no one will remember
役人は誰も覚えてないだろう
scientists remember
科学者は覚えています
This guy is a legend
この男は伝説だ
His name is Wander von Braun
彼の名前はワンダー・フォン・ブラウンです
got the name
名前をもらいました
who is it
どなた？
is the lead scientist of the V2 rocket.
V2 ロケットの主任科学者です。
big boss of v2 rocket
v2ロケットのビッグボス
He was never packed back by the Soviet Union
彼はソ連によって詰め戻されたことは一度もなかった
This is his later
これが彼のその後です
write in the field like this
このようにフィールドに書きます
I have always hated the Communist Party
私はずっと共産党が大嫌いでした
When the Red Army came in
赤軍が入ってきたとき
He hid in the box
彼は箱の中に隠れた
Does he know the Nazi king?
彼はナチスの王を知っていますか？
he hides first
彼は最初に隠れます
In a few months, the U.S. military will come
数カ月以内に米軍が来るだろう
he ran out
彼は走り出した
Hey, I'm here, I'm like this
ねえ、私はここにいます、私はこうです
America is like Huo Zhibao
アメリカは霍志宝のようなものだ
It's not like Huo Zhibao, it's the real Huo Zhibao
霍志宝とは違う、本物の霍志宝だ
just hurry him up
ただ彼を急いでください
Li Yu's please come to the United States to do a bigger cause
李裕さんはもっと大きな目的を達成するために米国に来てください
That business is called NASA
そのビジネスはNASAと呼ばれます
Is it early NASA
NASAは初期ですか？
when it was founded
設立されたとき
Can't say the biggest
最大とは言えません
Largest Engineering in Science
科学分野で最大のエンジニアリング
Actually, think about this
実際、これについて考えてみてください
history is weird
歴史は奇妙だ
he was a nazi
彼はナチスだった
And a high-ranking Nazi
そしてナチス高官
His companions were put to death
彼の仲間は処刑された
are war criminals
戦争犯罪者です
Either shot or hanged
撃たれるか絞首刑になるか
Not only was he not judged
彼は裁かれなかっただけでなく、
It is also very reasonable to invite to the United States to do a bigger cause
より大きな目的を達成するために米国に招待することも非常に合理的です
look how happy he is
彼がどれほど幸せか見てください
Do you have
ありますか
This is tantamount to saying that he led the first success here
これは彼がここで最初の成功を導いたと言っているのと同じだ
NASA was established at the end of 1958
NASAは1958年末に設立されました
The United States felt that we lost the first round
米国は第一ラウンドで負けたと感じた
extremely straight up
非常に単純明快な
We will use the power of the whole country
国全体の力を結集していきます
Founded NASA
NASAを設立
The United States lost the second round
アメリカは２回戦で敗退した
The second round is to send people to orbit
2 番目のラウンドは、人々を軌道に送り込むことです
or the Soviet Union
またはソ連
The third round is even bigger. Who landed on the moon?
第 3 ラウンドはさらに大規模になります。月に着陸したのは誰ですか?
can go back to the story we tell about the moon
月についての話に戻ってもいいですか
In the third round, both sides watched helplessly to see who would win.
第3ラウンドでは、どちらが勝つか、双方とも無力に見守った。
That's not something that can be done every day
それは毎日できることではありません
who sent a man to the moon first
最初に人間を月に送ったのは誰ですか
This is history, you know
これは歴史です、知っていますか
1969 US Apollo 1
1969年米国アポロ1号
crashed the moon
月を衝突させた
mr armstrong like go down there
アームストロングさん、そこに行ってください
That's one small step for me, one giant leap for mankind
それは私にとっては小さな一歩ですが、人類にとっては大きな飛躍です
that's the story
それが話です
The United States has been to the United States seven times in a row
米国は7回連続で米国を訪れている
succeeded six times
6回成功した
The USSR failed once
ソ連は一度失敗した
But he has logged in without anyone
しかし、彼は誰もいないのにログインしました
It's a success
成功だよ
But if you lose, you lose
でも負けたら負け
Don't say that you seem to lose half, there is no such thing
半分損しそうだなんて言わないで、そんなことないよ
you just lost
あなたはただ負けただけです
In 1972
1972年
Well
良い
both sides shouted stop
双方ともやめろと叫んだ
don't go
行かないでください
The reason is very simple
理由はとても簡単です
Aren't we running the 100 meters to see who wins?
誰が勝つかを競うために100メートルを走っているのではありませんか？
Have you ever seen someone running a 100 meters and still running?
100メートル走ってまだ走り続けている人を見たことがあるでしょうか？
no
いいえ
run until then
それまで走って
Win or lose is clear
勝ち負けは明らかだ
Even if you win, you don't want to run away.
勝っても逃げたくない。
If you lose, you don't even want to run away.
負けたら逃げる気も起きない。
The United States just doesn't want to run away.
米国はただ逃げたくないだけだ。
America really can't run
アメリカは本当に走れない
It's a waste of national power
国力の無駄遣いだ
It's not easy to do this kind of thing
このようなことをするのは簡単ではありません
this is very scary
これはとても怖いです
At that time it was still fighting in Vietnam
当時、ベトナムではまだ戦闘が続いていました
The two ends burn like this
両端はこうやって燃えます
Even though the country has put in all the power of Maoism to do it
たとえ国が毛沢東主義のあらゆる力を注ぎ込んでそれを実現したとしても、
But after doing it, it's really like running a hundred meters
でも、それをやってみると、本当に100メートルを走っているようなものです
worn out
使い古した
I'm exhausted. Don't do it anymore.
もう疲れたのでもうやめてください。
leave this one
これを残してください
We have been to the moon such a record
私たちは月に行ったことがありますが、これほどの記録はありません
yes
はい
then want to ask
それから聞きたいです
why are we going to the moon
なぜ私たちは月に行くのですか
I tell you no one can tell
誰にも言えないと言います
you see everything as if
あなたはすべてをあたかも見ているかのように見る
Going to the moon is so amazing
月に行くってすごいですね
It's just to see who wins
どちらが勝つかを見るだけです
Just run 100 meters
100メートル走るだけ
you really outperformed you are really amazing
あなたは本当に上回りました、あなたは本当に素晴らしいです
But do you want to ask that question
でも、その質問をしたいですか？
why should i run
なぜ走らなければならないのか
just want to win
ただ勝ちたいだけです
What about winning?
勝つことについてはどうですか？
How are you doing?
お元気ですか？
It's human psychology like this
人間の心理ってこういうものだよ
So what role does the moon play in this matter?
それでは、この問題において月はどのような役割を果たしているのでしょうか？
It's just that I was taken as a goal by you to fight for this
ただ、私はあなたにこのために戦うことを目標にされただけなのです
How much science is really done?
科学は実際にどれくらい完成されているのでしょうか？
a little bit
若干
For example, didn't you use the reflection technique just now?
たとえば、先ほどリフレクションのテクニックを使いませんでしたか？
just now
ちょうど今
And this one from Lantern Moon
そしてこれはランタンムーンのものです
I'll show you the back of my side first.
まずは裏側からお見せします。
Really some achievements
本当にいくつかの成果
brought back some stones
いくつかの石を持ち帰った
It can be analyzed that's right
分析できるよ、そうだね
And there is an earthquake chair left on it
そしてそこには地震椅子が残されています
It's not an earthquake, it's a moonquake.
地震ではありません、月地震です。
Really very few
本当に少ないです
Tiny really has moonquakes
タイニーは本当に月震を起こす
Isn't the moon dead?
月は死んでるんじゃないの？
How could it shake?
どうしたら揺れるでしょうか？
This can also be studied
これも勉強できる
Guess it's because of the tide
潮のせいなのかな
caused by the earth to its tides
地球の潮流によって引き起こされる
This is a scientific achievement
これは科学的な成果です
but you have to think about it
しかし、それについて考えなければなりません
How much effort was spent to follow the mining force, material resources, time, and manpower?
採掘力、物的資源、時間、人的資源を追跡するためにどれだけの労力が費やされましたか?
to do this? certainly not worth it
これをするのですか?確かにその価値はありません
so i secretly tell you
だからこっそり教えます
Daoyeqiu is not for science or human progress
Daoyeqiu は科学や人類の進歩のためではありません
It's a cold war to see who wins
誰が勝つかという冷戦だ
By the way did a little science
ちなみに、少し科学を勉強しました
so
それで
So is science worth spending so much money on?
科学にはそんなにお金をかける価値があるのでしょうか?
It's not worth it for us who do science
科学を行う私たちにとってそれは価値がありません
But he didn't say he wants to do science
でも彼は科学をやりたいとは言いませんでした
is in the international
インターナショナルにある
He wants to be the leader. He's the big brother of the western camp.
彼はリーダーになりたがっている、西側陣営の兄貴分だ。
he will do these things
彼はこれらのことをするでしょう
right
右
what's right or wrong? it's your judgment
何が正しいか間違っているか、それはあなたの判断です
OK, there are some behind this
OK、この背後に何人かがいます
I can tell you a fun story later
楽しいお話はまた後ほどさせていただきますね
But let's go back to what we were talking about
しかし、話していたことに戻りましょう
What did you say just now? It hasn't been resolved yet.
今何と言いましたか?まだ解決していません。
Why is the moon so wet for me
なぜ月は私にとってこんなに濡れているのですか
not yet
まだ
In fact, this truth has just been explained through the earth.
実際、この真実は地球を通じて説明されたばかりです。
Isn't our earth being turned slower and slower by its tides?
私たちの地球は、潮の満ち引き​​によって回転がますます遅くなっているのではありませんか?
you turn around
あなたは振り向く
The earth has tides on it, what's more powerful
地球には潮の満ち引き​​がある、それよりも強力なものは何か
the earth is so big
地球はとても大きいです
it's small
それは小さい
our tidal influence on it
それに対する私たちの潮汐の影響
although it has no ocean
海がないのに
But tides don't have to be in the water to happen
しかし、潮は水中にある必要はありません
It deserves the same friction as the ground. Squeeze what.
地面と同じ摩擦がかかるのです。
still the same friction
まだ同じ摩擦
we are so big it is so small
私たちはとても大きいのでとても小さいです
We have a big influence on its tides
私たちはその潮流に大きな影響を与えています
we'll make it spin slower and slower
回転をどんどん遅くしていきます
real
本物
What, how strong is it?
え、どれくらい強いの？
it stopped turning
回転が止まった
This can't be called
これは呼び出せません
It can't be the lowest energy
最低のエネルギーであるはずがない
it can't turn anymore
もう回転できない
It's called non-rotation
無回転といいます
The truth is the same
真実も同じです
Our friction with it
それに対する私たちの喧嘩
It's long gone
もう過ぎ去ってしまった
not now
今はやめろ
Don't say that it stopped turning dozens of years ago.
数十年前に回転しなくなったとは言わないでください。
so this is not a coincidence
だからこれは偶然ではない
it is
それはです
You can say it's exhausted
疲れ果てたとも言える
All the strength has been worn away by you
すべての力はあなたによってすり減りました
that's all
それで全部です
so it's no coincidence
だからそれは偶然ではない
So other angry stars and picture stars
だから他の怒っているスターや写真スターも
Its moons are all like this
その衛星はすべてこんな感じです
I don't know it stopped turning decades ago.
何十年も前に回転が止まったのかわかりません。
that's all
それで全部です
this is the answer to
これが答えです
We just started with that question
私たちはその質問から始めたばかりです
should be by now
今頃はそうなるはずだ
many questions just asked
たった今たくさんの質問がありました
already understood
すでに理解されている
ok now we can
わかりました、今できます
So back to a story we told at the end
最後に話した話に戻ります
This is the rocket that was used when the Apollo program was launched
これはアポロ計画の打ち上げ時に使用されたロケットです
This rocket is called the Saturn V
このロケットはサターンVと呼ばれています
really big enough
本当に十分な大きさ
This is the largest rocket ever made by mankind
これは人類がこれまでに作った最大のロケットです
Not this one, this series needs one every time
これではありません、このシリーズには毎回必要です
so big
とても大きく
When I got to that Washington, that's when I served there.
私があのワシントンに着いたとき、そこで奉仕したのです。
Every time I go to the US capital horse space museum
米国キャピタルホース宇宙博物館に行くたびに
All the NASA babes go in later
NASAの女の子たちはみんな後から入ります
great size
素晴らしいサイズ
it has a show want to show this thing
これを見せたいショーがある
At least show you how big this tail is
せめてこの尻尾がどれだけ大きいかを見せてください
right
右
To let you know wow, going to the moon was scary
うわー、月に行くのは怖かったです
how big is it
それはどれくらい大きいですか
It's too big, so there's no way to exhibit it
大きすぎて展示できない
very smart it looks like this
とても賢いです、こんな感じです
it uses a model
それはモデルを使用します
Just made such a small block
こんなに小さなブロックを作っただけです
then use the mirror
それから鏡を使ってください
a mirror over here a mirror over here
ここに鏡 ここに鏡
wow you go in and see
うわー、中に入って見ますか
wow it's so big
うわー、とても大きいです
In fact, this small corner
実はこの小さな一角、
very mirror very smart
とても鏡 とても賢い
really big big
本当に大きい大きい
Spray fire on this thing to go up like this
これに火を吹きかけるとこうやって上がります
why are you watching this
なぜこれを見ているのですか
I mean some people say it's a lie, right?
それは嘘だと言う人もいますよね？
Do many of you know
ご存知の方も多いのではないでしょうか
say someone will say
誰かが言うだろうと言う
It's a scam, never been there
それは詐欺です、行ったことはありません
Lie to you
あなたに嘘をつく
Nope, I've heard of bureaucracy
いや、官僚制については聞いたことがある
You must have heard of it, right?
きっと聞いたことがあるはずですよね？
good
良い
Then what I want to say is of course
じゃあ、私が言いたいのは当然です
Of course I've been there, don't be crazy
もちろん行ったことあるよ、怒らないでね
Is boring
退屈だ
This is the process of middle age
これが中年期のプロセスです
For example, this photo is famous
たとえば、この写真は有名です
Just for everyone to see
みんなに見てもらうためだけに
Here is this picture called Earthrise
これがアースライズと呼ばれるこの写真です
Sunrise Earthrise
日の出、地球の出
nor sunrise
日の出でもない
not Moonrise
月の出ではない
rising sun
日 地升
this is the surface of the moon
これは月の表面です
When actually orbiting the moon
実際に月の周りを周回しているとき
photo taken by the astronaut
宇宙飛行士が撮った写真
This is of course
これは当然です
Boss Aubrey he is the second
ボス・オーブリー 彼は二番目です
man on the moon
マン・オン・ザ・ムーン
he bowed his head
彼は頭を下げた
He said the angle of this photo is too important
彼はこの写真の角度が重要すぎると言いました
take a snapshot
スナップショットを撮る
it's famous of course
もちろん有名です
possibly human
おそらく人間
Don't know if the third or fourth footprint
3 番目の足跡か 4 番目の足跡かわからない
this
これ
I see too many pictures like this
こういう写真多すぎる
To be questioned is to say
質問されるということは、こう言うことです
where is this
ここはどこですか
this is the set
これがセットです
you are short
あなたは背が低い
You just take a photo on set
セットで写真を撮るだけです
help us
助けて
so you've been to the moon like this
それであなたはこうやって月に行ったんですね
no evidence
証拠がない
Then I can find a lot of holes
そうすると穴がたくさん見つかるよ
This is obviously something wrong with you
これは明らかにあなたに問題があります
that's wrong
それは間違っている
otherwise how could
そうでなければどうやって
you can't explain
あなたには説明できません
obviously you lied
明らかにあなたは嘘をつきました
this is what we heard
これが私たちが聞いたことです
This argument
この議論
Said that NASA has not actually been there
NASAは実際にはそこにいなかったと述べた
this is the set
これがセットです
Of course he told why
もちろん彼はその理由を語った
I really don't want to repeat
本当に繰り返したくない
Those concepts that those people say are wrong
あの人たちが言うその概念は間違っている
listen to you
聞いてください
because I'm wrong
私が間違っていたから
why keep emphasizing
なぜ強調し続けるのか
but roughly
でも大まかに
I can suggest some for you
いくつか提案させていただきます
Obviously you might find something weird
明らかに何か変なものが見つかるかも知れません
For example, it is dark
たとえば、暗いです
This is clearly under the sun
これは明らかに太陽の下です
isn't that right, the sun is clearly over there
そうじゃない、太陽ははっきりとそこにある
And it's bright, no problem
明るいので問題ありません
the sun is over there
太陽はあそこにあります
Why is the whole day dark
なぜ一日中暗いのですか
It's obviously a scam.
明らかに詐欺ですよ。
No, it's true. It should be black.
いや、本当です、黒のはずです。
Conversely, if this photo
逆にこの写真なら
If it's not dark here
ここが暗くなければ
Soon we'll know he's a liar
彼が嘘つきだとすぐにわかるだろう
it should be dark
暗いはずだ
am i standing there
私はそこに立っているのですか
you see the sun is bright
太陽が明るいのがわかります
Of course it's bright
もちろん明るいです
there is no sun
太陽がありません
how can it be bright over there
どうしてあそこが明るいんだろう
Of course it's black
もちろん黒です
It's not bright, it's black
明るくないよ、黒いよ
It's black over there too
あそこも黒いよ
Only that is bright, that's all
それだけが明るい、それだけ
Are you saying that this is not our experience?
これは私たちの経験ではないと言いたいのですか？
Let's go outside during the day
日中は外に出ましょう
The whole sky is bright
空全体が明るいです
No, that's the earth, it's weird
いや、あれは地球だ、奇妙だ
It's not the moon, it's weird
月じゃないよ、変だよ
What's so strange about the earth? Because it has air
地球の何がそんなに不思議なのか? それは空気があるからです
what you see is not the place that is glowing
輝いているのはあなたが見ているその場所ではありません
air scatters sunlight
空気が太陽光を散乱させる
become bright in all directions
四方八方明るくなる
the whole day is bright
一日中明るいです
that is the earth is strange
それは地球がおかしいということです
This is a function of the atmosphere
これは大気の関数です
The role of air
空気の役割
Including why the sky is blue
空が青い理由も含めて
That's the same reason
それも同じ理由だよ
It's the details inside
中身の詳細です
you can analyze it
それを分析できます
This was done more than a hundred years ago
これは100年以上前に行われたものです
people already know
人々はすでに知っています
This muyu scientist Raly
このムユ科学者ラリー
It's been proven
それは証明されました
So it should be dark this day
だから今日は暗いはずだ
No one dares to say that you are a liar, right?
あなたが嘘つきだなんて誰もあえて言わないですよね？
innocent is black
無実は黒人だ
It's like using a black cloth behind a black studio
黒いスタジオの後ろで黒い布を使うようなものです
But it was questioned where did the star go?
しかし、そのスターはどこへ行ったのかという疑問が生じた。
Isn't there a star?
スターはいないの？
Aren't you bright? There should be bright spots
明るくないですか?明るい部分があるはずです
Where did your bright spot go?
あなたの輝かしい点はどこへ行ったのでしょうか？
Apparently your black cloth is too...too...
どうやらあなたの黒い布はあまりにも...あまりにも...
Didn't you just drill a few holes and cheat... then you couldn't cheat?
数個の穴を開けてごまかしただけではないでしょうか...そうするとごまかしはできなくなりましたか?
No, because it's not easy for you to take pictures of those stars
いいえ、それらの星の写真を撮るのは簡単ではないからです
Because this is too bright, like the sun, really under the big sun
眩しすぎるから 太陽みたいに 本当に大きな太陽の下で
If you take out all the stars
星を全部取り出すと
Your exposure time has long been exceeded
露出時間をとうに超えています
throw it all away
全てを捨てて
I can't take a photo
写真が撮れない
Yes, but I'm sorry, I can't take a picture
はい、でもごめんなさい、写真は撮れません
In the Ganasa report when they came back
帰ってきたガナサの報告では
Many people have said that they see stars behind this photo
この写真の後ろに星が見えると多くの人が言っています
You can barely see bright spots
明るい部分はほとんど見えません
By the way, that's right
ちなみにそうですよ
There is also a very interesting one that can be used as a joke
ジョークとして使用できる非常に興味深いものもあります
it's called storytelling
それはストーリーテリングと呼ばれます
it is this
これです
This was also questioned
これも質問されました
And why is it like this on your ground?
そして、なぜあなたの地面はこのようになっているのですか？
You go to the beach and get some sand rabbits on that set
ビーチに行ってセットでスナウサギを捕まえる
then step on it
それからそれを踏んでください
wow that looks great
うわー、すごいですね
another lie
別の嘘
I'm telling you, I'm not lying
言っておきますが、嘘はついていません
I'll tell you later
後で言うよ
Why is it obviously not a lie
なぜそれが明らかに嘘ではないのか
this world is like this
この世界はこんな感じ
NASA people go before
NASAの人たちが先に行く
What does this big lunar surface look like?
この大きな月面はどのように見えるのでしょうか?
really do not know
本当にわかりません
because from a distance
遠くからなので
even around
周りでも
you can't see
あなたには見えません
what does the moon look like
月はどのように見えますか
but does it matter what it looks like
でも見た目は重要ですか？
Very important
とても重要
because you will log in in the future
将来ログインするので
that
それか
want
欲しい
thump
ドスン
right
右
that Taiwanese boat
あの台湾の船
This landing craft is about to land
この上陸用舟艇はまさに着陸しようとしています
if that is hard ground
それが硬い地面であれば
rock
岩石
wow then you like this
わあ、それならこれが好きですか
thump
ドスン
I really don't want that
本当にそんなことは望んでいない
Another is that the feet are not hard
もう一つは足が硬くないことです
all it can't get you...no mud
それはあなたを得ることができないすべて...泥はありません
because there is no water
水がないので
Otherwise it's sand
そうでなければ砂です
that's even scarier
それはさらに怖いです
How many feet do you go up like this?
このまま何フィート上がりますか？
Then it started to sink
それから沈み始めた
That's even scarier, right?
それはさらに怖いですよね？
so this is very important
これはとても重要です
not kidding important
冗談じゃなくて重要なこと
is really important
本当に重要です
Then why might it be a hard ground?
では、なぜ硬い地盤になるのでしょうか？
It is of course possible
もちろん可能です
Because when it was first formed, it was
なぜなら、結成当初はこうだったからです。
Rocks were formed four billion years ago.
岩石は40億年前に形成されました。
then what
じゃあ何
has he always been a rock
彼はいつも岩だったのか
Somebody go weather it into dirt?
誰かがそれをダートにウェザリングするのですか？
No
いいえ
Because there is no wind, no water, no air
風も水も空気もないから
it's hard
それは難しい
So that long didn't go before
だから、以前はそんなに長くはなかった
don't know what the surface looks like
表面がどうなっているのか分からない
must know
知っている必要があります
Because I want someone to go
誰かに行ってもらいたいから
So let's go to the moon with an unmanned one first.
それで、まずは無人で月に行きましょう。
I found it good
良いと思いました
not hard
難しくない
surface is dust
表面は埃だらけ
Not very thick
あまり厚くない
wow this is the best
うわー、これが最高です
So take the back seat and follow that
だから後部座席に座ってそれに従え
That kind of mechanics to do it, no problem, no problem at all
そういう仕組みでやれば問題ない、全く問題ない
That is to say, the surface of the moon
つまり、月の表面
really that's it
本当にそれだけです
What is this being questioned?
これは何を問われているのでしょうか？
What's up with the surface of the moon?
月の表面はどうなっているのでしょうか？
why is this
どうしてこれなの
I don't know why it happened in the early days
初期の頃なんでそうなったのか分からない
Scientists slowly study and think slowly
科学者はゆっくりと研究し、ゆっくりと考える
later found out that
後でそれを知りました
Since that's the case, let me explain
そういうことなので、説明させていただきます
explained
説明した
Makes sense yes
理にかなっています、はい
this surface is
この表面は
cosmic rays
宇宙線
An example of solar wind charging
太陽風による充電の一例
Been fighting for billions of years
何十億年も戦い続けてきた
It's all powdered
全部粉末です
Molecule by molecule for you
分子ごとにあなたのために
That's how it was after the fight
喧嘩後はこんな感じでした
It's not killing, it's not profit, it's like powder
それは殺しではない、利益ではない、それは粉のようなものだ
I would just describe him as dust, that's all.
彼を塵としか言い表せない、それだけだ。
The surface is really like this
表面は本当にこんな感じです
and in that video
そしてそのビデオでは
they're happy to go up
彼らは喜んで上ります
Jumping over there, right?
そこにジャンプするんですよね？
you have seen
あなたは見たことがあります
jump up and slowly fall down
飛び上がってゆっくりと落ちる
Because of the gravity on this
これには重力があるため、
Only one-sixth of the earth
地球のわずか6分の1
Of course you can jump high
もちろん高くジャンプすることもできます
Then this one falls very slowly too
それから、これも非常にゆっくりと落ちます
If you kick this powder
この粉を蹴ったら
will definitely kick
間違いなく蹴ります
You will also kick when you go up
上がるときも蹴ります
i promise you
あなたに約束します
You can see the gray in the video
グレーは動画で確認できます
That powder is like this
その粉はこんな感じ
slow down like this
このようにゆっくりしてください
This is also questioned
これも疑問視されてる
why do this
なぜこれをするのか
It's like there's air
まるで空気があるみたい
Actually, what I want to answer is to say
実は私が答えたいのは、
what do you think it should be
それはどうあるべきだと思いますか
as it should be
そうあるべき
no air
空気がない
if you say no
あなたがノーと言えば
then i know
それなら私は知っています
and you
あなたも
I haven't read ordinary physics yet.
私はまだ普通の物理学を読んでいません。
many questions
たくさんの質問
Actually, it's that kind, it's why it's so strange
実はそういうものだから不思議なんです
It seems different from the earth, so you lie
地球とは違うようだから嘘をつく
It's not like that, it's the other way around
そんなことはない、その逆だ
That's the truth, please think about it for yourself
それが真実です、自分で考えてください
Why is this so? After thinking about it, it should be like this
どうしてそうなるの? よく考えたらこうなるはず
It should be treated like this
このように扱われるべきです
Everything is true in the lunar environment
月の環境ではすべてが真実です
That's right, it's actually not easy to deceive people
そうだよ、人を騙すのって実は簡単じゃないんだよ
You really have to do a scene and do everything
本当にシーンを作り、すべてをやらなければなりません
It's all true, it looks weird
全部本当だけど、奇妙に見えるよ
In fact, they are all right. In fact, it is very difficult to do. I won't lie to you.
実際、それらは大丈夫です。実際、それを行うのは非常に困難です。私はあなたに嘘はつきません。
It's really harder to do
本当にやるのは難しいです
The moon landing started in 1961 when President Lee announced it on TV in public
月面着陸は1961年に李大統領が公のテレビで発表したことから始まった
Back then even the TV was a blackboard
あの頃はテレビも黒板だった
announced on tv
テレビで発表されました
Before the Coast of the Decade
我們10年の海岸の前
before 1970
1970年以前
we're about to put a man on the moon
私たちは人類を月に送り届けようとしています
and bring him back safely
そして彼を無事に連れ戻して
He will announce it to the world
彼はそれを世界に発表するだろう
And he's saying I ordered NASA
そして彼は私がNASAに命令すると言っています
Because NASA is the index of the presidential palace
NASAは大統領官邸の指標だから
So he made the declaration
そこで彼は宣言した
At that time, it was still fighting on the moon
その頃はまだ月で戦っていた
when i was working in america
私がアメリカで働いていたとき
some senior researchers
何人かの上級研究者
we sometimes chat
私たちは時々おしゃべりします
they'll talk about that time
彼らはその時のことを話すでしょう
They also saw it on TV
彼らもテレビで見ました
How does our boss make such a declaration
私たちの上司はどのようにしてそのような宣言をするのでしょうか
he's crazy
彼は気が狂っている
Do you think that even the computer at that time
当時のコンピューターでもそう思いますか？
nothing special
特にない
there's nothing left
何も残っていない
he's crazy
彼は気が狂っている
how can we
どうしたらいいの
NASA
NASA
only three years old
まだ3歳です
We'll be on the moon in a few years
数年以内に私たちは月に行きます
what are you kidding
何を冗談ですか
our boss is crazy
私たちの上司は狂っている
Our senior man said
私たちの先輩が言いました
they were at that time
彼らはその時にいました
Just the people in NASA
NASAの人たちだけ
their reaction is this
彼らの反応はこうだ
how about you go do it
行ってみてはどうですか
results in less than eight years
8年以内に結果が出る
just landed on the moon
ちょうど月に着陸したばかりです
this is
これは
this you want me to imagine
これを私に想像してほしいの
really can't imagine
本当に想像できない
how can it be so powerful
どうしてそんなに強力なのでしょうか
real
本物
when the power of the country is mobilized
国の力が動員されるとき
Wow
おお
the spirit of that america
あのアメリカの精神
really weird and powerful
本当に奇妙で強力です
none
なし
a nation
国家
or a group
またはグループ
can do this
これはできます
really weird
本当に奇妙な
America is not the first time
アメリカは初めてではない
Find a few more years in the 20th World War
第20次世界大戦があと数年続いた
Made it in three years
3年かけて作りました
it's hard
それは難しい
it's really hard to imagine
想像するのは本当に難しい
But how many years do you think this matter has invested a total of 100,000 people?
しかし、この問題に合計10万人が投資されたのは何年だと思いますか？
At that time, there were 100,000 people on Pangda Road
当時、龐達路には10万人が住んでいた
There are only 30,000 people now
今は3万人しかいない
How much money will the country go down
国はどれだけお金が減るだろうか
mobilize so much force
非常に多くの力を動員する
did it and succeeded
それをやって成功した
Do you think if this is a lie
これが嘘だと思いますか
you want the whole thing to be a lie
あなたはすべてを嘘にしたいのですか
want to face the truth
真実と向き合いたい
then fake
それから偽物
It can still deceive people on such a large scale
まだこれほど大規模に人々を騙すことができます
the degree of difficulty
難易度
you might as well go
行ってもいいかもしれません
real
本物
that is difficult
それは難しいです
it's not that hard for you to go
あなたにとって行くのはそれほど難しくありません
think from this angle
この角度から考える
In fact it is true
実際、それは本当です
I give you another test
別のテストをしてみます
maybe you know
たぶんあなたは知っています
right
右
you've been there
あなたはそこにいたことがある
this thing
このこと
You need to know the meaning behind them
それらの背後にある意味を知る必要があります
Just run white rice to see who wins
誰が勝つか白米を走らせるだけです
who lost
誰が負けたのか
Soviet Union
ソビエト連邦
People in the Soviet Union never said a word
ソ連の人々は何も言わなかった
No
いいえ
You know you're fake if you lose
負けたら偽物だとわかる
Who are you going to lie to?
誰に嘘をつくつもりですか？
The Soviet Union is full of experts
ソ連には専門家がたくさんいる
experts among experts
専門家の中の専門家
you got any fake stuff in here
ここに偽物が入っているのね
He's not the first to tell you to lie less.
嘘をつかないようにと言ったのは彼が初めてではない。
No
いいえ
Who is now talking about the United States?
今、米国について話しているのは誰ですか?
You go and look through those people in the future
あなたは将来それらの人々を調べに行きます
The more he talks the more money he makes
彼は話せば話すほどお金が増える
i will lie to you
私はあなたに嘘をつきます
write more books
もっと本を書く
more tv
もっとテレビ
The whole world invites him everywhere
全世界が彼をどこにでも招待します
i will lie to you
私はあなたに嘘をつきます
You will know why this kind of thing happens
なぜこのようなことが起こるのか分かるでしょう
If you have ever been deceived
騙されたことがあるなら
I guess you have enough curiosity
好奇心は十分あると思います
but sorry
でもごめんなさい
you are curious because you are curious
あなたは好奇心が強いから好奇心旺盛です
fact or fact
事実か事実か
This matter can be analyzed later
この件は後で分析できます
No matter what angle you say about dry shoes
乾いた靴についてどの角度から言っても
Is it human long-term love? Look at it from this angle
人間の長年の愛ですか? この角度から見てください
Don't worry, I've been there
心配しないでください、私はそこに行ったことがあります
it's all true
それはすべて本当です
OK this is the last one
OK、これが最後です
that is to say
つまり
Well, I was there at that time
そうですね、その時私はそこにいました
You know you've been there six times and you've been there at six o'clock
あなたはそこに6回行って、6時にそこにいたことを知っていますか？
There are instruments at six points
計器は6箇所にあります
There is the same path that the car on the moon surface traveled.
月面の車が通った道と同じ道がある。
There are traces all over
いたるところに痕跡が残っている
after decades
数十年後
are those things still there
それらのものはまだありますか
of course in
もちろんで
because there is no wind and rain
風も雨もないので
what was he like when he left
彼が去ったとき、彼はどんな様子でしたか
It's the same now. It hasn't changed.
それは今も同じ、変わっていない。
Then can we take a sneak peek?
じゃあちょっと覗いてみてもいいですか？
Can
できる
in 2009
2009年に
The United States sent a purpose not to see
米国は見ないという目的を送った
this original scene
このオリジナルのシーン
It's just some scientific satellites that we really want to explore.
私たちが本当に探索したいのは、いくつかの科学衛星です。
The spaceship is called the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
この宇宙船は「月偵察オービター」と呼ばれています
just went
行ったばかりです
Going around is going around without logging in
周回とはログインせずに周回することです
into my process
私のプロセスに
Of course those spacecraft have good cameras
もちろんそれらの宇宙船には良いカメラが付いています
Which means NASA, of course, has a schedule
つまり、もちろん NASA がスケジュールを立てるということです。
Someday you will fly to our original
いつかあなたは私たちの元へ飛ぶでしょう
Above the login point on the 11th
11日のログインポイントを越えて
you take our picture back
あなたは私たちの写真を取り戻します
Someday you will fly to the position of No. 14
いつか君は14番の位置へ飛んでいくだろう
Come back if you take a picture of me
写真撮ったらまた来てね
6 dots, 7 dots, all 6 dots are covered
6 つのドット、7 つのドット、6 つのドットすべてがカバーされています
All six points are taken
6点すべて取られる
Here are two examples
以下に 2 つの例を示します
this is
これは
left is
左は
11th is the first time
11日は初めてです
over there is number 14
あそこは14番です
Can you see a bright spot here
ここに明るいところが見えますか
the sun comes from here
太陽はここから来ます
here is a bright spot
ここは明るい場所です
its shadow is elongated
その影は伸びている
This thing is an upright tall thing
これは直立した高い物です
definitely not natural
間違いなく自然ではない
Natural things don't look like this
自然のものはこのようには見えません
except on earth
地球以外では
because when the wind blows and the rain
風が吹いて雨が降ると
time-lapse of that terrain
その地形のタイムラプス
It's possible to look long
長く見ることも可能です
That's what happens after erosion
浸食後はこうなる
normally it grows into
通常、それは成長します
don't grow anything like this
このようなものを育てないでください
here has
ここにあります
This is the point of the light path
ここが光路のポイントです
and see
そして見てください
An upright thing with such a long shadow
こんなに長い影を持った直立したもの
It's the Luna
それはルナです
this is stone town
ここは石の町です
that thing is still there
あの物はまだそこにある
Then you're a liar besides this
じゃあ君はこれ以外にも嘘つきだよ
All right
わかった
This is on the 14th side
こちらは14面です
look carefully
よく見て
Can you see there's a
があるのがわかりますか
There is that trace on this surface
この表面にはその痕跡があります
this is a spaceship
これは宇宙船です
space this one will go
これが行くスペース
What is a small car
小型車とは何ですか
out of the track
トラックから外れた
go put that instrument here
その楽器をここに置いてください
there are instruments
楽器があります
This shadow is also like this
この影もこんな感じ
this is current affairs
これは時事問題です
This is over 30 years
これは30年以上経ちます
stay safe
おげんきで
really still
本当にまだ
There is no need to keep saying this
これを言い続ける必要はない
i want now
今欲しいです
not talking about me
私のことを話していない
what do you want to prove
何を証明したいのですか
nope
いいえ
I told you back then that I never reacted
あの時は何も反応しなかったって言ったのに
no public announcement
公表はありません
didn't come out and say
出てきて言わなかった
Let me testify
証言させてください
we have been there
私たちはそこに行ってきました
I didn't say a word back then
あの時は何も言わなかった
never said
決して言わなかった
It's just that the official didn't say it back.
ただ役人がそれを言い返さなかっただけだ。
i think it's right
それが正しいと思います
casual talk
雑談
i don't care about you
あなたのことは気にしません
what do you mean
どういう意味
Really, you ignore him instead
本当に、あなたは代わりに彼を無視します
not like NASA
NASAとは違います
right
右
I dignified NASA
NASAの威厳を保った
I don't care what you say
あなたが何と言おうと気にしません
i have it
私はそれを持っている
I follow these
私はこれらに従います
not for
のためではない
to refute you
あなたに反論するために
I just want to take pictures
写真を撮りたいだけです
How about it
どうでしょうか
I just want to see the situation
状況を見たいだけです
This is the last trace left
これが最後に残った痕跡です
that's the end of my story
それでは私の話はここで終わります
Because of the moon you all start
月のせいで君たちは始まる
understand better
よりよく理解する
We humans probably know this too.
おそらく私たち人間もそれを知っています。
ok thank you all
わかりました、皆さんありがとう
Thank you so much
非常感謝
i think we really are
私たちは本当にそうだと思う
one night
ある夜
not talking about night
夜の話ではない
Learn more about the moon
月についてもっと詳しく知る
I also heard many stories
お話もたくさん聞きました
then we are left
それから私たちは残ります
about twenty minutes
約20分
let everyone ask questions
みんなに質問させてください
Doesn't China also have Tibet-Cooperative Moon Exploration?
中国にもチベットと協力の月探査があるではないか？
right
右
talk about
について話す
this right
これは正しい
In fact, if we say that this lunar exploration has been very quiet since 1972
実際、この月探査は 1972 年以来非常に静かに行われてきたと言えば、
Because what I just said is that there's nothing to go on
だって私が今言ったのは、何も続けることはないってことだから
sooner or later
遅かれ早かれ
Because you are curious about science
科学に興味があるから
During the Cold War, Japan actually had
冷戦時代、日本は実際に
These are small satellites
これらは小さな衛星です
even some are for experiments
実験用のものもあります
have been there
そこに行ったことがある
It really only started in the last few years
それは実際にここ数年で始まったばかりです
go back and say
戻って言う
we're going back to the moon
私たちは月に戻ります
have you heard the slogan
というスローガンを聞いたことがありますか
that is to say
つまり
It is to do this from the perspective of scientific exploration
科学的探査の観点からこれを行うことです
Well, I did make a statistic here.
さて、ここで統計を作成しました。
But the reason we have it is because it was years ago
しかし、私たちがそれを持っている理由は、それが何年も前のことだからです
look what's over here
ここに何があるのか​​見てください
It's not when you read my writing
あなたが私の文章を読んでいるときではありません
It was already a few years ago
もう数年前のことだけど
Actually quite a lot
実はかなり多い
Europe also went
ヨーロッパも行きました
Japan went to the United States several times
日本は何度かアメリカに行きました
Including most of China and Russia
中国とロシアの大部分を含む
I'm only going for the first time as I write
初めて行って書いてます
It's just Chang'e No. 1
まさに嫦娥1号です
Number three should be gone by now, right?
3番はもうなくなっているはずですよね？
that's gone
それはなくなった
haven't landed on the moon yet
まだ月には着陸していない
go to the moon
月に行く
But it will be more and more lively in the future, it's true
でもこれからますます賑やかになるのは本当だよ
Even India is going to go
インドも行くつもりだ
So this moon has become a new one
こうしてこの月は新しい月になった
Not a Cold War target anymore
もう冷戦の標的ではない
but
しかし
It's probably for the purpose of showing national strength.
国力を誇示するためだろう。
But unfortunately it still seems to be a goal
しかし、残念なことに、それはまだ目標のようです
Let me ask, the bigger the animal on the earth, the magnetic ring it walks on, like an elephant,
尋ねさせてください、地球上の動物が大きくなればなるほど、象のように磁気の輪の上を歩きます。
Obviously, there is no way to jump as high as an explosion, or as high as a jumping claw,
明らかに、爆発や飛び跳ねる爪のように高くジャンプする方法はありません。
Could it be that the earth used to rotate faster, so it has more centrifugal force,
もしかしたら、地球は以前は自転が速かったので遠心力が大きかったのかもしれません。
Then the moon is on it again, and it is pulling, so the dinosaurs more than 100 million years ago can grow to be so big,
そして、月が再びその上にあり、月が引っ張っているので、1億年以上前の恐竜は非常に大きく成長することができます。
Then after the dinosaurs died out, it would be better if you couldnt grow up to be as big as a dinosaur,
だったら恐竜が絶滅した後は恐竜ほど大きくならないほうがいいのに、
Because the earth rotates relatively slowly now, there is no centrifugal force.
現在、地球は比較的ゆっくり自転しているため、遠心力は存在しません。
In this way, what you think of this seems to be quite interesting qualitatively,
こうやって考えると、定性的にはかなり興味深いように思えますが、
However, this should not be the case in terms of quantification. That is to say, you just mentioned these phenomena,
しかし、これは定量化の観点からは当てはまらないはずです。
We actually understand it, I will describe it a little later,
私たちは実際にそれを理解しています、それについては少し後で説明します、
But the phenomenon you mentioned, in fact, no matter how fast our centrifugal force is on the earth, you actually dont feel it.
しかし、あなたが言及した現象は、実際には、地球上の遠心力がどれほど速くても、実際にはそれを感じません。
That centrifugal force is now only 1/300 of Wanyous profit.
その遠心力は現在、万友社の利益のわずか 1/300 にすぎません。
not yet
まだ
no matter how fast you earn
どんなに早く稼いだとしても
That's like one hundredth
それは100分の1くらいです
that's going to happen soon
それはもうすぐです
That's like one hundredth of gravity
それは重力の100分の1のようなものです
That's only one hundredth
それはわずか100分の1です
How big can that grow for animals
動物にとってそれはどれくらい大きくなるでしょうか
that effect is too small
その効果は小さすぎる
Then you say that the difference between animals is several times
そうすると動物には数倍の差があると言うのですね
several times
何度か
That's only one percent off
それはたったの1パーセントの割引です
It is really
本当にそうです
negligible
無視できる
So it has nothing to do with that reason
だからそんな理由とは関係ないよ
how fast with that
それはどれくらい速いですか
it doesn't matter
それは問題ではありません
Then why did dinosaurs grow so big
ではなぜ恐竜はあんなに大きくなったのでしょうか？
We can now also fear
私たちは今、恐れることもできる
If you bite a dinosaur now, it can be this big
今恐竜を噛むとこんなに大きくなるの？
but you'll find it's really slow
でも、本当に遅いことがわかるでしょう
Even an elephant can say it's slow
象でも遅いと言える
Moves very slowly compared to Jumping Claw
ジャンピングクローに比べて動きが非常に遅い
The jumping claw is dozens of times taller than its own body
跳躍爪は自身の体の数十倍の高さがある
Or an elephant, or if you are on the road in a powerful scene, or something with a big road, just jump off
象とか、迫力あるシーンで道路上とか、大きな道路があるものなら飛び降りてください
This is not, it has nothing to do with whether the earth rotates or not
これは地球が自転するかどうかとは関係ありません。
This is because under our gravity
それは私たちの重力の下で
The bigger the thing, its volume, for example, you magnify me ten times
大きいもの、その体積、たとえばあなたは私を10倍に拡大します
My weight has changed a thousand times, but my feet have only grown a hundred times
体重は1000倍も変わったが、足は100倍しか伸びていない
This is two-dimensional space, the volume is three-dimensional space
これは 2 次元空間、ボリュームは 3 次元空間です
You magnify me ten times, you see I am big, and my feet are a hundred times bigger
あなたは私を10倍に拡大すると、私は大きくなり、私の足は100倍も大きいことがわかります
But sorry, I'm a thousand times heavier
でもごめんなさい、私のほうが何千倍も重いのです
do you think i can stand still
私がじっとしていられると思いますか？
So what should I do? Then my legs will be thicker
じゃあどうすればいいの?そうしたら足が太くなるよ
It can't be enlarged so thick according to my scale.
私のスケールではそこまで厚く拡大することはできません。
Elephants are like this, you see their legs are so thick
ゾウってこんな感じです、足が太いですね。
seems out of proportion
不釣り合いに見える
That is to say, you dance him
つまり、あなたは彼を踊ります
Speechless, ask him to zoom in
言葉もなく、ズームインしてもらいます
don't say he dances
彼が踊るとは言わないでください
he can't even stand
彼は立つことすらできない
his thin feet
彼の細い足
so in that movie
だからあの映画では
how to explode
爆発する方法
mouse so big
マウスの大きさ
don't be afraid
恐れないでください
he won't eat you
彼はあなたを食べません
he can't even stand
彼は立つことすらできない
this is just
これだけ
The difference between two tails and three tails
二尾と三尾の違い
There are actually many examples of this
実際にこのような例はたくさんあります
we look up at the sky
私たちは空を見上げる
because of the sky
空のせいで
this space
この空間
air this
これを放送する
Microparticle
微粒子的
spectrum turns blue
スペクトルが青に変わる
on the night ball
夜の舞踏会で
see what color it is
何色か見てください
good question
良い質問
We see the blue of the sky is
空の青さは
in our big air
私たちの大きな空気の中で
The solution to scattering sunlight
太陽光の散乱に対する解決策
if you look from the outside
外から見たら
Actually you can't see the air
実は空気は見えないんです
it is transparent
透明です
we are in this because
私たちはこの中にいます、なぜなら
it fan shot
それはファンショットです
it fanned in
それは煽られた
not outside
外ではない
outside is getting thinner
外側が薄くなってます
from the outside
外部から
good question
良い質問
when viewed from the outside
外から見ると
In fact, the air is transparent
実は空気は透明なんです
no air in sight
空気が見えない
but we can see
しかし、私たちは見ることができます
clouds in the air
空気中の雲
clouds are white water
雲は白い水です
water molecule
水分子
it's not by fanning
煽ることによるものではありません
it is reflection
それは反省です
It's just a group of white clouds
それはただの白い雲の集まりです
elsewhere is
他の場所は
If you don't see the land
土地が見えないなら
or the sea
または海
that's all
それで全部です
did not see
見ませんでした
also can't see what color it should be
また、何色にすべきかもわかりません
On the whole
概して
our earth
私たちの地球
Nicknamed Blue Planet
愛称はブループラネット
mean blue planet
青い惑星を意味する
That blue is not because of the air
あの青さは空気のせいじゃない
It's the reflection of sea water
海水の反射です
there is another reason
別の理由があります
why is the sea blue
なぜ海は青いのか
That's another reason, but it's really blue
それは別の理由ですが、本当に青いです
70% of the earth is water
地球の70％は水
So the earth as a whole looks like a blue shape from the outside.
そのため、地球は外から見ると全体として青い形に見えます。
Please tell me, you said that the earth is also angry with the moon
教えてください、地球も月に対して怒っているって言ってましたね
This means that the interior of the moon is not solid either.
これは、月の内部も固体ではないことを意味します。
That's a good question, the moon we think it's something that's cooled
良い質問ですね、月は冷却されたものだと私たちは考えています
But it is completely solid, why does a solid have friction?
しかし、それは完全に固体であるのに、固体にはまだ摩擦があるのはなぜでしょうか?
The answer is yes, solids still have friction
答えは「はい」です。固体にはまだ摩擦が存在します。
Because the energetic society outside is actually pinching and pulling it with images like this
なぜなら、外のエネルギー社会は実際にこのようなイメージでそれをつまんだり引っ張ったりしているからです
In this molecule and molecule, there is actually a mole-mole movement.
この分子と分子の中で、実際にはモグラとモグラの動きが存在します。
That's how Momo energy is consumed
モモのエネルギーはこうして消費される
So this optical translation is friction
つまり、この光学的変換は摩擦です
So don't look at his hard one still inside
だから彼の中にまだ硬いものを見ないでください
Just now there were earthquakes and moonquakes
さっき地震と月地震がありました
are the result of this force
この力の結果です
Ask Professor Zhao
趙教授に聞く
The one who read the report that there was a sign of water found on Mars
火星に水の痕跡が見つかったという報告を読んだ人
also have air
空気もある
So it's a bit similar to the conditions on Earth.
つまり、地球上の状況と少し似ています。
Very suitable for human migration to Mars
人類の火星移住に非常に適している
Ask Professor Zhao for your opinion
趙教授に意見を聞く
Thanks
ありがとう
good question
良い質問
But you want me to live, I don't think so
でもあなたは私に生きてほしいと思う、私はそうは思わない
Because what you said is very suitable is actually just a relative
だって君が言ったとても適当なことは実はただの親戚だから
Which means he's at least not as hot as the sun
つまり、彼は少なくとも太陽ほど熱くないということです
Or maybe the pressure isn't as great as Jupiter's
それとも圧力が木星ほど大きくないのかもしれない
Or maybe he doesn't have that much gravity
それとも彼にはそれほど重力がないのかもしれない
i can stand up
私は立ち上がることができます
It's okay in terms of
という点では大丈夫です
Because Mars is the size of Earth
火星は地球と同じくらいの大きさだから
not too much difference
あまり違いはありません
so its
っていうことは
the gravity you are on
あなたが乗っている重力
smaller than the earth
地球より小さい
Great
素晴らしい
people go to dream shape
人は夢の形へ向かう
you can't stand
あなたは我慢できない
just go down
ただ下ってください
that gravity is too much
重力が大きすぎるということ
there are others
他にもあります
it has air
空気がある
but sorry for its air
でもその空気はごめんなさい
all carbon dioxide
全て二酸化炭素
you can't breathe
息ができない
its temperature
その温度
kill you
あなたを殺してください
because it is far
遠いから
and the earth is far away
そして地球は遠く離れています
and
と
Even if it's all carbon dioxide
たとえそれがすべて二酸化炭素だとしても
its
これは
greenhouse effect
温室効果
only raise it to
まで上げるだけです
Some
いくつかの
still too cold
まだ寒すぎる
Of course the air is only of the earth
もちろん空気は地球のものだけ
Less than 10%
10%未満
very thin
非常に薄いです
is there any water
水はありますか
Now there is no liquid water on the surface
今、表面には液体の水はありません
because it's too cold
寒すぎるから
it maybe that
それはもしかしたらそれかもしれない
Soil can't be called soil
土は土とは言えない
The weathered sand
風化した砂
Those substances may have frozen moisture in them
それらの物質には凍った水分が含まれている可能性があります
might have
持っているかもしれない
In particular, there is a lot of dry ice in the North and South Poles
特に北極と南極にはドライアイスが大量に存在します。
it's cold
寒いです
Does that mean it's a good place for people to live?
ということは人が住みやすい場所なのでしょうか？
In fact, it can be said that you go up
実際、上がっているとも言えます
I don't talk about you
あなたのことは話さない
you put a person on it
あなたはその上に人を置きます
He died in three minutes
彼は3分以内に死んだ
he can't be hot
彼は熱くなれない
Then you say I want to build something
それからあなたは何かを作りたいと言いました
The airtight environment keeps fire inside
密閉環境により内部に火がこもりません。
of course you can
もちろんできます
then you can also be on the moon
そうすれば月に行けるよ
The elite can't come up with it
エリートにはそれが思いつかない
too hot to kill you
死ぬほど暑すぎる
Look at it from your fake angle
偽の角度から見てください
Oh well
しかたがない
That Mars is
あの火星は
If you must leave the distance
距離を置かなければならない場合
you choose him, you don't choose anything else
あなたは彼を選びます、あなたは他には何も選びません
It's not that he's good, other things are worse
彼が良いというわけではなく、他のことがもっと悪い
The professor just heard that the earth will turn slower and slower because the power of his feet is absorbed by the moon
教授は、足の力が月に吸収されるため、地球の回転がますます遅くなるだろうと聞いたところです
Then there is a question that I didnt understand just now, why is he always seeing the same side of the moon
それから、今は理解できなかった質問がありますが、なぜ彼はいつも月の同じ面を見ているのですか？
Then why is it because the moon is no longer spinning, so he can see the same side of him
では、なぜ月が自転していないので、彼は自分の同じ側面を見ることができるのでしょうか？
It's not because the power of his feet is absorbed by the moon, why isn't the moon turning faster and faster
足の力が月に吸収されるからではない、なぜ月の回転がどんどん速くならないのか
Great question for this question this has a strong physics concept
この質問には素晴らしい質問です。これには強力な物理概念があります。
I was just secretly wanting to... just... pass the door like this
ただ密かに…ただ…このままドアを通り抜けたいと思ってたの
In fact, this means that the foot momentum is taken away by him, so shouldnt he turn faster and faster?
実際、これは足の勢いが彼に奪われていることを意味するので、彼はますます速く回転すべきではないでしょうか？
If it's fast, it's not... sooner or later I'll see behind him
速いかというとそうではない...遅かれ早かれ彼の後ろが見えるだろう
This didn't happen because
こんなことは起こらなかったのだから
the shape of the moon
月の形
Has been sucked into a very strange shape by our earth
とても奇妙な形に私たちの地球に吸い込まれてしまった
It's not that you think it's weird when you see it, it's not weird
見ていて変だと思うわけではない、変ではない
It still begs for a ball
まだボールを求めています
look inside carefully
中を注意深く見てください
it becomes a bit out of shape
少し形が崩れてしまいます
it faces the earth
それは地球に面しています
It turned out to be like the one in Zhongbai
中白のものと似ていることが判明しました
this is the lowest one
これは最低のものです
You can say Veen, Gravity Veen
ヴィーン、グラビティヴィーンって言ってもいいよ
its shape has been taken by the earth
その形は地球によってとられました
It seems to be frozen
凍ってしまったようです
so it just
だからそれはただ
when you go around like this
こうやって回ると
it's very comfortable
とても快適です
Now you have to force it to turn faster
今、あなたはそれをより速く回転させる必要があります
In fact, there is another force
実は別の力がある
want to pull it back
引き戻したい
So now put in an extra effort
だから今はさらに努力してください
or Earth's tidal forces
または地球の潮汐力
please don't turn
振り向かないでください
because you like facing me
あなたは私と向き合うのが嫌いだから
Because this shape already looks like this
この形はすでにこんな感じなので
So its final result is
したがって、その最終結果は次のようになります
it's still like this
まだこんな感じです
But the foot momentum is still there
でも足の勢いはまだある
what about it
それはどうですか
The result of this balance of forces is that everyone starts to turn in a big circle, just like that
この力のバランスの結果、みんなが大きな円を描き始めて、そのまま
It is said that NASA has taken photos of aliens, is this really the case?
NASAが宇宙人の写真を撮影したと言われていますが、本当にそうなのでしょうか？
Who said NASA ever took pictures of aliens?
NASAが宇宙人の写真を撮ったことがあるなんて誰が言った?
no , you smash that tv
いいえ、あなたはそのテレビを壊します
If there is really a TV saying that, you can really sue him for slander or nonsense
本当にそう言うテレビがあるなら、誹謗中傷やでたらめで本当に訴えればいいのに
So I'm someone who used to be NASA, I want to really blow him up
だから私はかつてNASAだった人間です、彼を本当に爆破したいのです
It's a joke of course, but the point is you don't really don't say anything
もちろん冗談だけど、大事なのは本当に何も言ってないってことだ
Just do what you say, no, you have to make your own judgment
言われた通りにやればいい、いいえ、自分で判断する必要があります
how to judge
どのように判断するか
listen to speeches more
もっとスピーチを聞いてください
That nonsense is too much
そのナンセンスは多すぎる
we have one more question ok
もう一つ質問があります。
let him that one
彼にそれをさせてください
Hello Professor I have a very curious question
こんにちは、教授、とても興味深い質問があります。
These are the names you mentioned just now
これらはあなたが今挙げた名前です
Why is it so consistent with the names of the five elements we Chinese talk about?
なぜそれが私たち中国人が話す五大元素の名前とこれほど一致しているのでしょうか?
how is this so consistent
これはどうしてそんなに一貫しているのですか
not this is the same thing
これは同じことではありません
That is to say, we are the same as the ancients
つまり、私たちは古代人と同じなのです
now people are the same
今では人々も同じです
If you want to find planets in the sky
空の惑星を見つけたいなら
The planets are recognizable
惑星は認識可能です
because it can run
走れるから
The other stars are always a place
他の星はいつも場所です
You can watch it move when you turn it yourself
自分で回すと動く様子が見られます
But planets relative to other stars
しかし、惑星は他の星と比べて
it is moving
それは動いています
moving so close to me
私の近くに引っ越してきました
You can see that its position is moving relative to other stars every day
他の星に対して位置が毎日移動していることがわかります
In fact, in English, the word Planet means a heart that can run
実は英語でPlanetという言葉は走る心臓を意味します。
Then let's say translated into planets, it will go
それから惑星に翻訳すると、それは行きます
People in ancient times were not called planets, they were called Huo Xing, Huo who was confused
古代の人々は惑星とは呼ばれませんでしたが、混乱した霍星、霍
because I really don't know why it moves
何故動くのか全く分からないので
Others are not moving, this fan
他の人は動かない、このファンは
Even if we were in history, you are the same now
たとえ歴史上にいたとしても、あなたは今も同じです
You go to the sky to find Huo Xing, you can find five
霍星を見つけるために空に行くと、5 つ見つけることができます
can be seen with the naked eye
肉眼で見ることができます
The Chinese people's method is five, well, gold and wood follow Huo Tu
中国人のやり方は五、金と木は霍図に従う
Who? Who is gold, that yellow one is called gold, that gold star
誰? 金は誰ですか、あの黄色いのは金と呼ばれます、あの金の星は
Who is wood, who is fire, that spark is fire
誰が木で、誰が火で、その火花は火です
because it's red
赤いから
Who is the water, the white one
水は誰ですか、白いのは誰ですか
It's Mercury, the other two are Jupiter and Saturn
それは水星、残りの2つは木星と土星です
This is how it came about, because we originally had the concept that gold and wood follow Huo Tu
このようになったのは、もともと金と木が霍図に続くという概念があったからです。
and saw five guys in the sky
そして空に5人の男が見えた
Then give him a checkmark
それから彼にチェックマークを付けてください
Then we have the concept of yin and yang
次に、陰と陽の概念があります。
that's even better sun moon
それはさらに良いサンムーンです
All seven guys got it right
7人全員が正解しました
Then this lived happily for thousands of years
それからこれは何千年も幸せに暮らしました
until the nineteenth and eighteenth centuries
19世紀から18世紀まで
the telescope is out
望遠鏡が出てきました
see not only five but six and seven
5つだけでなく6つや7つも見る
There are eight, even the earth is one
八つある、地球も一つ
So what to do, this is completely broken
それでどうするか、これは完全に壊れています
It's our original philosophy
それが私たちの本来の哲学です
This arrangement doesn't actually work
この取り決めは実際には機能しません
No, we now know that's not right
いいえ、それが正しくないことは今ではわかりました
just a coincidence
ただの偶然
So those names come from
それらの名前の由来は
rather than just
ただではなく
you just follow him
あなたはただ彼をフォローするだけです
So how do we name the new discovery?
それでは、新しい発見にどのように名前を付けるのでしょうか?
i run out
足りなくなった
just use
ただ使ってください
Just use English or what Westerners call you
英語か西洋人の呼び名を使ってください
I just translate the meaning
意味を訳しただけです
Urnus is the king of heaven
ウルヌスは天の王です
Is Nephtune really the god of the sea?
ネフチューンは本当に海の神なのでしょうか？
It's Aquaman
アクアマンだよ
Is Proctor really that Yama of Hell?
プロクターは本当に地獄のヤマなのか？
It's King Ming
明王です
The name came from outside
名前は外から来ました
Then we originally gave the golden wood decaying European soil
それから私たちは最初に黄金の木にヨーロッパの腐った土壌を与えました
Foreigners also have these five names
外国人にもこの5つの名前があります
They don't call gold, wood and Europe
ヨーロッパの土壌が衰退したのは金木とは言わない
He called this this this this this this
彼はこれをこれをこれと呼んだ
Then we now say Venus is Vinus
それでは、今ではヴィーナスはヴィーナスであると言います
Mars is Mars
火星は火星だよ
it's the same thing
それは同じことです
that name is different
その名前は違います
It was different
違いました
It's almost a process like this
大体こんな感じの工程です
we really enjoyed it tonight
今夜は本当に楽しかったです
Everyone go out later
みんな後で出かけよう
At least I saw the moon when I came
少なくとも私が来たときは月を見ました
when you go out to see the moon
月を見に出かけるとき
do you feel different
違うと感じますか
Uh uh thanks everyone
ああ、みんなありがとう
Thanks
ありがとう
good teacher
いい先生